<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-ouija-board</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84028296/1886-04-29/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE NEW TALKING BOARD.
Tfce
MjitarlMS AaBaaeaaeat Which la
raeelaattBt; Okls reettltk
Many of our readers will still remember
planchette, the strange little heart-shaped
board with a pencil at its point which used
to walk over yards of paper and write no and
of tenie and nonsense if the finger tips of two
persons touched the upper surface of the
board. .
Planchetts had Ka day, and mostl died
out But the same mysterious force which
used to impel it it moving now another kind
of little board, and setting whole eommuni
Uet of eminently sober and respectable Ohio
people on their heads. ,
You see how it it made. A bit of board,
say 18x30 inches, is lettered, rather large,
with the alphabet, A, B, C, D, etc The
letters are put a small distance apart At
the upper corners of the board are written
the words : yes and no, the yes on tha
left, the no oa the right On tha left and
right hand lower corners respectively are
written good evening and good night
Underneath tha letters of the alphabet are
the figures in a row, the whole arranged like
thit:
. : tesV  , no. - :
j ABC OS VGH I JKL MIf : 
ibPQBSTUVrVXVK., :
. 1334T8V0 i
 Good-eve.
Good-night
Hen a tiny table it made with four legs.
It is three or four inches high and very thin
and light Two persons tit opposite each
other and take the board upon their knees at
in the picture. The little four-legged table ia
placed upon the board. The two persons
grasp tightly with the thumb and forefinger
the comers of the table that are next to them.
TBS TAXKXJfQ fJOABDb
The two sit down and become quiet, asking
rtioml After a few minutes the little table
begins to move over the board, It is an In
tel lig nt, or at least, a semi-intelligent force
that guides : the table, for it answers
questions. Bomettmes It talks utter nonsense
and again it will write real information.
The table spells out sentences in this way.
When a question is asked, the table moves
towards the tetters, and the foot stops upon
the first one of the sentence to be written out
Then it passes to the next one and the next
and so on, with more or less rapidity, a
gentleman, who hat experimented with the
thing, says: Sometime the table will cover
two letters with Its feet and then yon hang
on and ask that the foot be moved from the
wrong letter, which will be done,
One man who tnougnt nit lamiiy was
spending too much time over the talking ma
chine burned it up. . Then he left noma on a
Journey. When the talking board could not
be found some one made anotner, ana tne
amusement went on. as before. To tho qu
tion what had become of the other board the
answer was given, Jack burned It up,
which somewhat astonished Jack on his re
turn. .
The questions may be asked mentally, even
by persons sitting in the room several feet
away from the operators, and tha answers
are given Just as readily. Ia some cases re
markable and truthful revelations are said to
have been given about living persons. But it
it not well to girt too much heed to these
revelations.
  </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82016373/1890-12-21/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn94052989/1893-11-14/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WEIRD WRITINGS.
The Planchette Craze Has
Broken Out Again.
UNSEEN FORCES AT WORK.
Some Uncanny Pranks of a Little
Instrument That Once Held the
Attention of the World.
There Is a planchette fever in San Fran
cisco.
Clubs of patient sitters, anxious to hold
communion with the dead and distant liv
] ing, have been formed here and in Oak
land. Daily and nightly seances are being
! held.
Plancbette is old, so old that it is almost
new again. Early in the fifties the weird
! little contrivance was invented and ten
< years later nearly the whole civilized world
was teaming with a recital of its wonders.
The most uncanny tales were related of
the marvelous doings of the instrument,
and for a time the greatest scientific minds
of the world were interested iv its queer
pranks. Such men as Tyndall and Faraday
were drawn Into controversies pro and con
over the merits of this occult agency.
Exhaustive essays were written and
learned lectures delivered to < prove that
planchette was a fraud and to prove that
planchettes powers were supernatural.
But it all ended where it began. The
deepest study and the most careful analy
sis of the wiles and ways of planchette
developed nothing of scientific value either
to the student of the occult or the natural
forces.
And so the planchette fever died as
quickly as it had grown. Men and women
went back to their workaday world or con
tinued their occult studies unuer different
auspices. Planchette had it« little day nnd
! then died a natural death. Or, if it did not
i die entirely, it lapsed into a slate of coma
j from whicn it is only now being resur-
I rected. To-day, in San Fraucisco aud in
j Oakland, and perhaps In other parts of
| ihe world, great numbers of men and
: women are bent on solving the mysteries
i that still cling to this little contrivance.
| And it is all because of that irrepressible
j desire of man to penetrate the mysteries
j of the future. ; f ,v :<
What does to-morrow hold for me.
That is the question nearest the heart of
most men to-day. lt is a very part of the
commercial spirit of the age. And as yet
science has made no advances toward
placing the means within reach of answer
ing it. So planchette comes again to fill
the gap between the known and the un
known.
What started the fever no one seems to
i know. Hint it has been started and has
already interested hundreds of intelligent
men and women no one doubts, for the evi
dence is clear.
You know what planchette is, do you
j not, and how it operates? Some have
] thought there was a hidden secret in its
I construction, but this is wrong. Never
was a wonderful device more simply con
trived; There is first a heart-shaped cedar
board. Pendant from the points of the
! angle are little legs with metal or wooden
! castors. At the end of the board is an
| aperture for the insertion of a lead pencil.
Those who fit to planchette for communi
cations from this world or the next place
a baud each on the surface of the board,
then wait till the spirit moves. And
the spirit has been moving pretty rapidly
in these parts of the world for the last
few nights. Dire things have been fore
told and timely warnings given.
Ordinarily planchette will write out
what it has to say if time be given i\ but
the quicker way is to write the alphabet
and the simple negative and affirmative on
a large sheet of white paper and let plan
chette spell out its messages by pointing to
tbe letters.
It was this method pursued py a party
of well-known clubmen who began as
i skeptics Friday evening and went home at
I daybreak firmly convinced that there were
i at least many things that they had little
j dreamed of In their phiiosophy. Only two
members of the party placed tbeir hands
on the instrument at one time. The others
j looked on and scoffed.
We were all unbelievers when we sat
down to that table, said the member of
the party who told the story to a Call
man yesterday. For a while planchetie
refused to move and we were almost on
the point of giving it up for the night,
when, without un Instant warning, the in
strument gave a sudden jerk and almost
flew from uuder the fingers of Jones and
Smith.
Roth the men turned pale at this and
in order to rally themselves they accused
each other of having moved the planchette.
On their honor both men denied this, but
since neither had believed his own accusa
tion the denials were useless.
I think it was a wife or a sister of
Jones that came first.  I bave forgotten
the name of the spirit or influence, or
whatever it was, that purported to move
the instrument, but the information it im
parted can be easily verified or disproved
when the next news from Samoa arrives.
It spelled out Apia first, very clearly
and unhesitatingly. Then it went on to
say that a terrible hurricane would sweep
over the Samoan Islands on the 10th of
November and that two vessels would be
lost In the storm. And touching this
event it would say no more, : though we
plied it with queries for a long time.
Another influence came. I remember
tbe name, but shall not give it.
 Dead or living? asked Smith.
 Living, came the answer, but Smith
knew this already, for the name it gave
was the name of his sweetheart.
 What have you to tell me? queried
Smith, and then he wished he had not,
for the answer that came distressed bim
sorely. .
Twill not marry you, it spelled out
with painful accuracy.
 Why not?, was the natural question
that followed when Smith had recovered
his presence of mind and bad determined
to face it out.
 Because I like D— letter, came the
answer.
Then two men glared at each other for
a moment, for D— sat at the opposite end
of the table waiting bis turn to try plan
chette.^^StHß^^B^o96iQHSK^
Now, if It were not already notorious
that D— hail been a little soft on Smiths
sweetheart of late we would have passed
over this little incident as one of the
vagaries of plancbette. But Smith couldnt
take it in this light. He was crushed, and
Invited D— to take his place. 1 neednt
tell you that D— declined the invitation,
but I would stake a small sum that D—
has his bands on a plancbette this moment.
a,\*l look Smiths place at the planchette
and presently the thing ; began ;to move
again. This time it discarded the use of
the alphabet and gave its message in writ
ing. . .- .. ■-.\  ■
Now, I am not going to place any reli
ance on this thing till I see how it turns
out, but the message that came to me is
Important if it is true.
I am an enemy, it wrote.
Are you going to thrash him? asked
Jone?, who likes to be facetious when
there is the least call for it.
.No! said • planchette. Then after a
pause it carefully wrote out, 1 am going
to harm him. - : He is my enemy and - I will
be revenged.
Well, all this meant nothing without a
name, and no name had been given yet.
Again I asked for the name and ■it not
only wrote oat the name of tbe man who
happens to be smarting under a very just
punishment that i Inflicted upon, him, but
wrote it in bis own handwriting. - a 
, You should have seen some of the faces
of the men who sal about that table when
they recognized the handwriting. One of
the men who bad . laughed loudest  and
scoffed the most when we first sat down
found it necessary to go outside for fresh
air. There was no more laughter tbat
evening. i -•-. - ■--•
Then it came into my bead to ask plan
chette something about itself, but before
we put the questions both Jones and my
self were blindfolded. This precaution is
unnecessary, for it is simply impossible to
move planchette as it does move without
exerting a physical force that would be
readily detected. However, we did this
more to convince ourselves than others.
.Are you inspired? asked. 
Yes, came the answer.
 By a good power?
The instrument fairly flew to the word
no.
 By the devil said Jones.
 The devil, it spelled out without the
least hesitation. :}; s: 
 Who are you? I inquired.
An agent of the devil, replied plan
chetie, and this time in writing.
And after that there was not a man in
the room brave enough to put bis hand on
that instrument.
The above questions and answers can
be vouched for by -more than one man
whose word in the commercial world is as
good as his bond, and many similar dia
logues might be cited to prove— prove
well, to prove that plancbette has a strong
hold on the people of this city once more.
Whether the craze will die out before it
reaches any great proportions again re
mains to be seen.</text>
    </result>
    <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058396/1915-12-11/ed-1/seq-17/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Tho oulja board Is coming back
; : tnto favor and has been taken up
I quit extensively by society women
v In New York, Boston, Chicago, St.
Louis and various parts of the coun
try.  Perhaps tho most remarkable le-
Iccnt experiences with it arc those of
Mrs, John Curran of St, Louis. Sho
has been in communication, she says,
with the spirit of Patience Worth, a
woman beliovcd to have existed in
lhe Colonial days and who not only
has sent philosophical axioms that
are characteristic of tho Puritans
but even has gone to tho extent of
sending outlines of plays and es
says and has gone extensively Into
the dictation of poetry. More than
300,000 words havo been received
from this supposed spirit in ihieo
years.
Patience Worth talks In a strange
; t English that is archaic and not
J 1 found in the best authors and yet
j may have at one time been the
tongue of Inhabitants of this coun
try. Long condemned by religious as
the direct agency of satan and by
i skeptics as the toy of the supcrsti-
tlous, the ouija board is being ro
f stored to its own former popularity
I through the curiosity of society wo
men. In many parts of the country oo
clety women are devoting their timo
to communicating with spirits in
tho other world.
Many stiango results of such com
munications are reported and a ao
t clety woman is unhappy indeed if
she hasnt at least one good spirit
i in tho world of mystery who is al
B) ways ready to send a message at her
m, controls pleasure.
Ill Even in staid St. Louis where so-
lit! cIety women arc supposed to bo
! 1$ very conservative, tho ouija board
il has been, restored to favor whilo
HA
-
in New York and In various
cities of the east it is quite the
rage.
In St Louis Mrs. John H. Curran
has gotten into touch with one Pa
tience Worth of Spiritland and has
transcribed more than 300,000 words
thiough the ouija board, all of which
will be published at some future
date.
Patience Worth is believed from
her peculiar choice of words and
phraseology to be a Colonial dame,
who has been wandering about In
space for a long time, burning to
send her messages back to the mun
dane sphere yet finding no source of
communication until Mrs. Curran
bought a ouija board and com
menced taking messages.
THROUGH
CURIOSITY.
The board Avas purchased through
curiosity. There is something fas
cinating about the tales told of tho
little board, whether they be- true
or false. It is known that a num
ber of people have asked the board
to tell them in what land their dead
iclativcs liugercd and were shocked
considerable- when the naughty Utile
hoard spelled out a word starling
A ith an H and ending with an L.
Many have thought that the words
written bv the board were the result
of the mental influences oC the per
son opeiating it. while others have
credited it with supernatural pow
ers. In tho use of tho board at the Cur
ran home, Mrs. Curran always is one
of two whose hands are on the
board. The latter is arranged on
two wheels and has a pencil at the
end. As the vibration of the fingers
of tho holders develops the pencil
moves over a sheet of paper and
prints numerals or letters of the al
phabet, While Mrs. Curran operates tho
board her husband transcribes tho
message as sho reads it to him.
The Patience Worth matter be
gan to be transcribed in June, 1913.
Since that time Mrs. Curran has
made public as the products of Pa
tience Worth a six-act play entitled
Red Wing. a novel called Tclka
and numerous verses, essays and
bits of philosiphy.
The quaint language of these writ
ings has probably attracted more at
tention than their literary merit, tho
latter being a matter of some dis
cussion. They are in an antique
language, not the English of Chau
cer, Spenser or any other well-
known classic English writer, but
possibly more like the common
speech of the English people of an
early day.
It is known to travelers that an
antique, almost archaic, form of
English still Is spoken in remote
communities of England. Theie are
districts of England whose inhabi
tants have great difficulty in under
standing or in making themselves
understood by the coster-cockney
class.
Mrs. Curran, however, says sho
has no personal acquaintance with
such speech and that she has not
gone farther in her study of classic
English than other well read per
sons. The language used by Patience
Worth, she explains, is as strange
to her as It is to others.
Mrs. Curran recently gave to the
Fapyrus Club of St. Louis some of
her messages from Patience Worth,
one of them being a special messago
that Patience had sent the club. It
read:
PATIENCE WORTHS
MESSAGE.
Good Dames and SIrrahs At the
board thou hast sat and cat of
earths grow. Aye, and now do ye
cat o the grow thou knowest not the
looting place of. Yea, thou shalt
hark unto the woid o MEN, and jet
they do to prate o DAME. Ayca,
and methlnks tis a word aspoke
amany, that be not the word that
hid pon the lung, lest the Dame be
offended I
Aye, then come thou and ait bout
the board, and thine cars shall hark
tmto the words o me, and thou shalt
sec the cloth o me the hands o the
loves o mc did to fashion out for
me. Ayea, I then shall sit me meek,
and thread mc up a bobbins full for
the next o put.
Ayca, and tis frocked that I shall
to be, and nay dame shall see!
Awoe! Nay, this be a piddlc-put-tlng,
good folk!
Athin (within) thy heart shall set
the me o me at thy go ahence. And
tis nhope I be tis a loving wampth
twill find. And so dost thou to
smile, tis Bweets and love 1 cast
thee. And doth thy heart to shut it
up, lo, then shall I to knock till thou
dost leave me in.
A night o cheer. A heart o love!
A Gods wish o loving pon thy day.
Anight! Anight!
HOW IT
BEGAN.
Mrs. Curran told her audience of
her first experiences with tho ouija
WW
w !
board and of the puzzling messages
received. Later sho used theboard
together with Mrs Emily Grant
Hutchings and began to receive
sentences which foimcd maxims and
philosophical paragrapbs. Then
came the announcement:
Many moons ago I lived. Patience
Worth, my namo. If thou shalt live
then so shall I. I make my bread by
thy hearth
The word bread. Mrs. Currau
later learned, lefeired to the literary
products embodied in the messages.
Mrs. Curran said she would not at
tempt to say whelhcr Patience
Worth was a spirit, but spoko of ,ber
as a beautiful personality, which had
come to seem not a mystery but a
fellowship.
She said the messages came to her
in daylight as well as at night and
that there is no trance connected
with them.
The words come in sort o a
rhythm, Mrs. Curran explained,
and I record just what comes
whether I understand it or not.
Pnticuce has been tested by rnoro
than 200 persons and her messages
have never varied. A professor from
the University of Indiana visltod
Mrs. Cunan to investigate her com
munication with Patience Worth.
William Marion Reedy, editor of
the Mirror, and Caspar Yost, editor
of a SL Louis newspaper, became ac
quainted with Patience Worth and
both declaic her genuine. Yost has
described her as a spinster of un
certain age; a writer, but a poet by
preference. White the average spirit
stalks dismal and wailing lugubri
ously through the flnito world, Pa
tience comes with a laugh, Yost said.
She remarks. I be no sorrj singer,
and proves it by many witticisms.
EDITOR
DESCRIBES HER.
Reedy calls Patiences doctrines
Pantelstic.
 He describes her as follows: She
fs a little woman, dressed In gtaj;
with a little bonnet, ribbons coming
down and tied under her chin. There
are lines in her face, not the re
written wrinkles of the smiles or
her youth, but the results of ex
perience Her eyes are biown liico
autumn leaves after a rain. She Is
-between 45 and 50 years old, spright
ly, dainty, delicate.
Sho has stood beside the stock
ade helping a good man load a gun,
while he defends the settlement
against the savage horde of In
dians. Reedy said the theory was ad
vanced that she was filled in an In
dian massacre and this question was
askcu of her. Sho intimated that
something of this sort had happened
to her and she was asked if she had
not been taken captive oy the In
dians. Nay, something worse, was her
reply.
.She speaks an English almost
pure and undefiled, Reedy said of
her There is an absence from it
of all the derivatives of France and
Rome, and sho rarely uses a word
of more than two syllables. Her an
swers are- diredt and almost invari
ably in parables. She has respect
for her interlocutors intelligence.
Reedy said sho is not another
Sappho, or George Elliott, or Mrs.
Humphrey ward nor a Sara Teas
dale, but rather echoes of all of thct
poets. He said theie runs a consist
ent character through her works and
in two years she has not gotten out
of chaiactcr. Sho never has used a
modern word or expression and he
illustrated the seeming significance
of this by pointing out how difficult
it would be for a man trained In
Irish or negro dialect to make a 30
minute talk without breaking out of
the character.
She has nothing lo tell, in my
opinion, Reedy said, but she com
mands my admiration and reverence.
She tells nothing- that we have not
heard from tho old masters and
bards.
What of the divinity of Christ?
Kcody at one time asked her through
the ouijd board. She answered, He
bought thee of his loving.
What of love? he asked. Tho
love there is but tho oer drip of lovo
here came the respou&c of tho
board.
Describe tho place where you
are? sho was asked. Think you
Patience Worth, Mythical
Character, Startles Literary
World With Her Quaint I
English In Essays, Plays and H
Novels Noted Writers Are H
Puzzled Over the Output of H
This Woman Supposed to H
Have i Lived 300 Years Ago H
there Is bottom or top; this is a
walless country.
Can you do anything you want
over there 7 The answer was:
When you put the will you put the
limit.
Put in Patiences vocabulary re
sponds to the modern verb to do.
Patience may be a second person
ality of Mrs. Curran, -Reedy sato.
but she teaches a lovo that is
greater than we can conceive and
that death is the keeper of unknown
redemption.
LITTLE COLONIAL
DAME.
Mrs. Emily Hutchings, who -was
one of the first to receive with Mrs.
Curran the messages from Patlenco
Worth, said the first glimmering or
the quaint personality of the little
Colonial dame came in the maxim:
A busy saw gathereth no rust.
One of the sentiments expressed
by Patience Worth is: A blighted
bud may hold a sweeter message
than the lovllest flower; for God
hath kissed her wounded heart and
left a promise there.
Of the seances, Mrs. Curran says:
I sit with a friend, our hands up
on the board, which I havo come to
believe is nothing more than a con
centrator. There is no trance. Ev
erything is quiet with the exception
of Patience Worth. The only
definite part is that while I put my
thoughts awhither, as Patience
would Bay, and immediately the sto
ries, poems, plays., parables, or
whatever her work for the sitting IH
may be, is shown to mo in tiny pic- JH
lures, beautiful and distinct a3 IH
though my eyes saw them.
The characters move and speak H
and my hands fly over the letters jH
much too fast for me to anticipate- H
even one word. J
I cannot account for the langu- jH
age. The words seem to be spoken ilH
to me. though I cannot say 1 hear llH
them In the sense that we hear tho iH
voice that speaks aloud to us. The H
words come m sort of a rhythm. I lH
am not familiar with old Euglish jH
and yet even the conversations -are H
in this archaic tongue. jH
Psychologists recently havetakcn ,H
up a study of Mrs. Curran and tho M
Mvstcrlous Patience Worth. Some jM
believe that Paticnco Worth is Mrs. jH
Currans sub-conscious self. Others jH
have departed in doubt and without jH
expressing an opinion. iH
The ouija board has been con- JH
demned by various religious bodies, iH
but society is taking it up beside il
these prohibitions. The Catholic tl
church has condemned it as a super-
stitlous practice. H
Other religious bodies havo u- H
clarcd that the devil is in hc boaid H
and employs it to send his messages. H
Whatever the truth may be, so-
ciety has gone into the mystery of lH
tho board, not so much with the ob- iH
jeet of definitely deciding if it really jH
is the medium of communication H
with the other world but to,gratlfy H
societys chief attribute Curiosity. H</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1915-12-12/ed-1/seq-33/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WHAT THE OUIJA BOARD IS.
The ouija board is a board about two and one
half ieet by one foot The letters of the alpha
be* are pa nted upon it in two concentric BC9
cirdes, and the numerals fren one to zero ap
pear or. a straight line beneath; in the upper
l;ft hand corner appears the word nay, and
la the upper right hard corner the word yea.
The messages are spelled out by means ota
small triangular shaped pointer resting upon
three legs, shed tritt felt to prevent rasping on
itching the board. At this hoard Bit!
Mrs, Cuiran wilh arvbody who may be in*
tereste-d enough to alt with her. The sitc
rest their fingers upon the triangular pointer
en it moves about among the Icters?
r,g out words with a mar?cl!, v.s rLp.d.ty.
The operations ?re conducted in a par!
fully lighted. Mrs. Curran is not blindfolded
Anybc?dy present is at full 1 berry to make any
investigaticns the situation may suggest or
to ask any questions It make? DO d..:erenc;
at what t.rre Mrs. Curran and her vis-?-vr. s.t
dotrn to the board; the pointer begins to Bash
about and messages are reoe ved from Patience
Wert1?. These messages are taken down by
Mr. John Howard Curran and preserved in a
record which now estends to nearly 5,00,000
wcrtis.
      </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1919-11-23/ed-1/seq-71/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn96076839/1920-06-25/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WHO INVENTED OUIJA
Brothers Ask Baltimore Court to
Settle Dispute.
Brothers, Apparently Lacking Falfh
 In Talking Board, Ask Judge
to Decide.
Baltimore. At the moment that the
oulja board, which some years ago ex-
cited the country and then virtually
disappeared, has again come Into the
Umellgbt throughout the world, two
brothers are engaged In litigation here
over the ownership of the patent, t
The trial Is now In progress of the
, suit of Isaac Fuld, trading as the
Southern Toy company, who I ask
ing for an Injunction to restrain his
brother, William Fuld, from deriving
pecuniary profits through the sale of
the oulja board.
The plaintiff asserts that In 1904 he
originated, manufactured and placed
upon the market the board under the
copyright name of the oracle and
that later William Fuld started the
manufacture of ihe oulja board.
William Fuld asserts that he and
Isaac Fuld were In business together
years ago, and that the oulja board
Is the original talking board, and
claims that tlie oracle talking board
manufactured by Isaac Fuld Is a
copy of the one placed on the market
by him.
The Fulds about 28 years ago were
In charge of a wooden toy factory
known as the Kennard Manufacturing
company, and the oulja board was one
of the devicesthey made to entertain
the young. It quickly won tremen
dous popularity nnd so overshadowed
the business of tho concern that the
plant was largely devoted to the mak
ing of. the oulja board.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1920-01-25/ed-1/seq-32/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063381/1920-02-24/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1920-11-14/ed-1/seq-70/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE ouija board has invaded
Britain! It masquerades un?
der the pseudonym of plan?
chette, but it is the familiar
alphabet and flatiron device that has
helped to while away the tedium of
prohibition in the United States.
And apparently it has landed in
force, because even now officials of
womens clubs are debating as to
whether the planchette is a game,
or, if it isnt, what it is.
If it is a game. argued one club
secretary, it should be played as a
game In the cardroom and during
the regulation card hours. As it is,
the planchette enthusiasts are busily
occupied with their favorite pastime
from early morn to dewy eve.
Although she waxed poetic at the
end, it was evident that the official
 was really disturbed about the exact
status of the planchette. F->r it is
said that the fascinating business of
receiving messages from the spin*
world?not the s?ance which was w
popular following the war, but the
more informal question-and-answer
of the ouija board?is quite ousting
the card games.
If no regulation planchette is at
hand a substitute, consisting of ?B
ordinary inverted tumbler surround?
ed by cardboard letters, is CtB*
into play. The fingers are pl??*11
upon the bottom of this glass, j^*
as they are upon the little triant
lar device of the real ouija boaru.
and it skips lightly from one letf*r
to another spelling out its message*.
And the planchette is less ex?
pensive than bridge, because no on*
yet has thought of betting on tM
spirits! . -?j</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1921-10-26/ed-1/seq-22/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>18 the 0uga Rosn MA8
Mental Trounble i
Washington?
By BILL PRICE.
Whether there is truth in a statmmnt that the ouija
board is adding patients to Wasinta asums
through disturbing infinenoes augon District mentalitin,
students of mental phenomena will be inteAsted in the
fact that the board takes its name from the French
word oui (yes) and the German word ja (yes). Its
origin is somewhat obscure. Both the planohette and
ouija, somewhat simila in appearanes, date back to
about 1855, and for a while were objects of consider
able superstition. The planchette is a small board
fitted with a pencil and two casters, made to move
easily over a sheet of paper when the hands rest lightly
on it. The dictionary says the ouija is a form of
planchatte used in spiritualistic seaness or the like.
It consists of two parts, a board containing the al
phabet and other characters, and a planehette, with
a pointer substituted for the pencil.
Investigation of automatic writings fail to find that
the two boards have any origin in the mysticisms of
Egypt. One writer is of the opinion that the iret at
tempt in ouijaing was made by a man on his wifes
breadboard. The skeptical refer to the board as
wholly a modem trick afair which has no connection
with Eastern or other metaphysics.
Some of the noted spiritualists of the world make use
of the ouija or planchette and carefully study the *
results. An able group of psychologists regard the
ouija as a dangerous deception. Their theory is that
the subconscious mind of the operator directs the
fingers in such a way as to convey the information
hoped for. The operator, they hold, is as innocent of
this subconscious process as a sleep-walker is of what,
he is doing, and naturally puts a supernatural con
struction on the outcome.
Leading spiritualists and other believers in higher
agencies than natural ones, confident that communica
tion with the other world is not only established but
is developing into an understanding that will glorify
humanity, are willing to accept the ouija board or any
other method of transmission that will add ti the in
formation they feel they now possess. Those of ma
terial minds, who deride all supernatural beliefs and
theories, hold to the opinion that after every great
war there is a wave of the occult in some form, and
say that right now the ouija board happens to be the g
most popular man-made medium of bringing together
terrestrial pinds and celestial beings and thoughts.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024827/1922-06-06/ed-1/seq-1/</id> 
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
	   <result>
	   <!--extra document 1-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87058235/1920-04-28/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 2-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024808/1920-02-27/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>AN INTERVIEW WITH OUIJA.
Washington, D. C., Feb. 23.—"Why
don't you interview ouija?" asked a
friend the other day.
We thought it over. Our relations
with "weegee" have always been rather
distant. We have met at parties and
at the homes of ouija fans. But always
we have passed the time of day in a few
trifling queries, and let it go at that.
Certainly, we never expected to start
interviewing spirit celebrities so long as
the earthly supply held out.
Still, we reflected, there were advan
tages to this kind of interview. Ouija,
once cornered, could not plead a previous
engagement or a conference, and judg
ing bv his reputation he would have a
lot to say.
So we decided to borrow a staid, ser
ious minded old ouija and ask him about
the Sims-Daniels scrap, and who ought
to be the next president, and if there
were any messages from cousin Lon,
who is either dead or in Chicago. We
knew the very board to borrow. It be
longs to an elderly lady who goes in for
higher thought and concentration, and
undoubtedly Jier ouija has never been
asked a silly question in its life.
The old lady promptly offered to get
the board, and also a book on how to
get the best, results with ouija. We
hauled ouija home, corraled a /riend to
act as accomplice, and with the setting
arranged, settled down for the interview.
First, howecer, we read the book care
fully. We found out that "the solar
plexus—that never sleeping brain of the
individual—is the switchboard or receiv- j
ing station for the messages." We also j
discovered that "the great secret why
some individuals can successfully use the '
board and some cannot is that the suc
cessful person must have, so to speak,
a diseasedly sensitive solar plexus."
That worried us. as our solar plexus has
always been pretty healthy, and we
feared the message germs might not
have any effect. For a while we held
on to the hope that maybe the writer
was mistaken about the solar plexus be
ing the brain of the soul, but further
on we found that ouija himself had told
her, "The solar plexus is the spiritual
brain." With this inside information
and a warning that to get best results
you must think high thoughts we invited
"little weegee" to the interview.
For the property of a higher thought
sort of person this ouija board certainly
had a remarkable line of talk and in- ;
teresting opinions. It told us that there •
would be a big war in 1982, that ouija :
meant spirits, and it advised us to "for-,
get it" when we politely inquired if it j
had a message for us.
After a rest it condescended to tell'!
us that Aunt Harriet, who died some j
years ago is very happy, but when we i
asked for Dûmes to come and tell us ;
who was the man in the iron mask, it j
wouldn't write anything except, "They '
don't answer."
When we returned the board we eon/ 1 - ;
meuted on the rather flippant attitude ■
it seemed to have. "Well," said the old
lady. "I never tried this board myself
It's the maid's board."
Having talked to "little weegee" we !
decided to find out something about his
life history. The messenger at the pat
ent office was frankly amused at our
mission.
"Weejail ?" he repeated with a huge S
grin. "Yassah. Try de toy division, '
sub."
The toy division was also moved to
laughter over the password, but soor
recovered sufficiently for a pleasant iyoung patent examiner to get out a col
lection of the patents.
"There are about 30 or 40 patents
along this line," he explained. "Some
are ouija board type, worked by a mov
ing index, and others are planchettes and
have a pencil to write the message.
"The first ouija board, called "little
wonder," was patented around 1868.
Since then, the idea has been adapted
and the board improved by numerous in
ventors, mostly toy makers. The ouija
board and similar inventions can be
patented in the United States only as a
toy. The patent office does not inquire
into any mystic properties, and it does
not permit inventors to claim or de
scribe such properties in their patent
papers."
In England, however, Inventors often
go into detail to explain the supernormal
power of such devices. Thus, one Brit
ish patentee inserts the following on j
his patent:
"If the person or persons are of a |
temperament suitable for the reception !
of spiritualistic or telepathic messages, ;
sentences may be spelt out obtained from !
such sources and possibly conveying in
formation unknown to the operators;
the larger number of messages, how- j
ever, are automatic, i. e., communica- j
tions from the subliminal consciousness j
finding expression through muscular ,
workings controlled in a method hither- i
to only imperfectly understood." j
"What does ouija mean, anyway?" we'is
asked the Patent Office, for we have ,
heard all sorts of cabalistic meanings at- j
tached to the queer syllables. !
"Well," said an obliging clerk, "the !
name is trade marked just as a word,
but we understand that it means "yes,
yes," being derived from oui, which is
French for yes, and ja. which is German.
This seems plausible, if we discount
ouija's own statements that its name
signifies "The Master's Hand," or "The
Fnknown," or that it is Hawaiian for
"Truth." If ouija had not told so manyj
people such different names for itself it'
might be easier to believe that the word
savors of the occult. As it is, we fear
that some prosaic toy maker, French
perhaps, or Oermau, accidentally put
these two syllables together and found
the effect pleasing, so that he named the
board which answered yes und no. ouija,
a union of languages not offensive to i
anvooe in those davs. j
The ouija board most used in the Fn- |
ited States was patented bv William
Fuld, a Baltimore toy manufacturer. Mr.
Fuld invented his board simply as a game :
j
of the puzzle or mystic varietv. He is!
very careful to say that he does not .
claim any remarkable powers for his :
invention, but, on the other hand, he
tells the public that he docs not himself
know exactly what makes the little table
move in so uncanny a fashion. j
This Solomon-like verdict is the only
safe one for the inventor, for to deny
outspokenly that his little board held
any kinship with spirits would greatly j
injure the trade in his best seller, while ;
if he claimed mysteriotfS powers in league
with the bits of wood, then he might be
held responsible for some of little ouija's
playful jokes.
Take the recent case of a woman who
was unable to account for the disap
pearance of a sum of money. Ouija told
her that a certain neighbor had taken it.
and this startling advice was accepted
as a clue from heaven. The neighbor
was dramatically accused of theft, and
the case went to court, one woman
claiming a charge of theft, and the other
The Invested Capital of This Bank
Is now three times the original capital stock of
$125,000, due to safe and careful management.
Behind this big margin of safety stands the
Federal Reserve System, of which we are mem
bers. The Federal Reserve is justly regarded
by world authorities as the strongest banking
system of any nation.
GREAT FALLS NATIONAL BANK
"Strength and Service"
ESTABLISHED 1881
after a libel suit. In such an instance
the inventor of ouija is safe from at
tack as the cause of it all. as he never
claimed his invention was infallible.
Most of ouija's history has been com
P( ]y, g0 far, and a good deal has been
farce, but in a few cases au unaccount
able force is said to have guided the
hoard. The outstanding example of this
the well known story of Patience
Worth who sent messages to a St. Louis
woman through a ouija board. The
mystery of Patience was that she talked
in the language of the seventeenth cen
tury England, using words and figures
of speech which the medium could not
possibly know, but which were almost
always found in dictionaries of archaic j
English. Patience is still a mystery—a
seventeenth century English spinster
who came to St. Louis to give her poems
tary had gurgied our message to him be
tween fits of giggles, easily heard over
the phone. The chief clerk was amused,!
too. but the third commandment of the
government is to give a serious answer
to inquiries.
to the twentieth century, and for social :
chats with the medium and her friends,
all through the ouija board.
We had talked to the ouija board, and
delved into its history, and there was
one more thing we wanted to know about
ouija—how does it work, anyway. We
called up the Bureau of Standards, the
government's scientific laboratory. The
chief clerk answered, after his secre
"Of course," he said, "we have neyer
made a study of this matter. I noff,
cially. I should say that there is a tend
ency for the eye to guide the little ab.e
toward some letter The influence < of
the eye is shown m that it is almost im
possible to get any results blindfolded.
"les. he concluded, it is probably
the working of the sub-conscious mind,
Still, we wonder. Thousands of P e J>
pie pla y with the board every nig.it
— -</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 3-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn90059959/1920-05-01/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 4-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063496/1920-01-15/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 5-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88078751/1922-12-05/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 6-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85042243/1920-08-23/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Mirth overwhelms him
mention the ouija board.
For the jolly chap is J.
mons, "Ouija King."
lie can afford to laugh. For the
people are buying the ouija boards lie
makes so fast that he's rolling in
money.
Sim-
Laughs at Public
'.'The public are fools!" laughs the
'Ouija King."
"They'll bite on anything'," he con
mues. "The public befjef 'Sn 'the
mijii_ board is a joke. Wo don't l'os
'.er it. But flic poor deluded fools
.vant the board find we're' giving: it
-the^i by the thousands.'*k
Tlis past year 500,000 ouija boards
were £ld by J. M. Sjiiimooa & Co
nade a little second-floor factory
.vith 10 employes on Chicago'* West
•iide. Simmons said :is. muny- moiv
•vere sold by the. William Fultl Com-1
«xry of Baltimore.
Does "Ouija KingifV. Simmons use
he ouija board himsfeltV He does
•ot.
Womlrrs as Future
If the man who makes the ouija
eally thought the ouija had any mys
\i« pOKer Jiu would sit right down ant!
sk the ouija to tell him whether the
niija craze is going to hist through
the winter.
And—precisely quoting Mr. Sim
amis:
"1 'ain't such a fool as to waste
my time asking the ouija questions
i'otit the (-raze. Gosh, thought! I'd
like to know whether the fool public
is going to yell for the ouija board
next winter. Its hard
%to
get the
three-ply lumber stock the boards
ire made out of unless you order it
long in advance. 1 don't know wheth­
er to order lumber or»not."
Simmons probably will take a
•hanee. For he's moving, into a fac­
tory four times as big as the old one
And if the ouija fails him/he'll go
back making toys.
lis' (lie Kunk, He Says
Simmons s.iys ho doesn't foster
mystic .belief in the ouija. Yet the
lirections he pwts out contain 'these
statements:
".Many scientists claim this
board does ,not answer questions
from an unknown power that,
its 'animation' frows.ffom per­
sonal magnetism. Spiritualists
claim that invisible' spirits
guide its movements, d?*superior
intelligence ruling our future.
"If you fail to get resists' in
playing the board, it is at no
time the fault of the board. It
is merely that the so-called
psychic force is' undeveloped in
the operators. Ill that</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 7-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn98069867/1920-03-16/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>AN INTERVIEW WITH 0UIJA
BY FREDERIC J. HASKIN.
WASHINGTON. March 16. "Whv
don't you Interview ouija?" ascked a
friend the other day.
We thought It over. Our relations
with "weegee" have always been rather
distant. We have met at parties and
at the homes of ouija fans. But al
ways we have passed the time of day
In a few trlflipg queries, and let It go
at that. Certainly, we never expected
to start interviewing spirit celebrities
so long as the earthly supply held out.
Still, we reflected, (here were advan
tages to this kind of interview. Ouija,
once cornered, could not plead a pre
vious engagement or a conference, and
judging by his reputation he would
have a lot to say.
So we decided to borrow a staid, serious-minded
old ouija and ask him
about the Sims-Daniel scrap, and who
ought to be the next president, and If
there were any messages from cousin
Lon, who is either dead or'lh Chicago
Ke knew the very board to borrow. It
belongs to an elderly lady who goes in
lor higher thought and concentration,
and undoubtedly her ouija has never
been asked a silly question in its life.
The old lady promptly offered to gat
the board, and also a book on how to
get the best results with ouldja. We
hauled ouija home, corraled a friend
to act as accomplice, and with the set
ting arranged, settled down for the In
terview. First, however, we read the hrmli
carefully We found out that "the solar
plexus that never-sleeping brain of the
individual Is the
reiving at-uinn for
also discovered th
ne switchboard or re
for the messages " We
son e i nd v U I. 2L SKa 2SB I
use the board and some can not Is Mat
the successful person must have, so to
FT! P41y sensitive solar
' " f'u!' ' That worried us, as our solar
lllf'"s has always been pretty healthy
i an1 we feared the message germs might
not have any effect. For 'a while we
held on to the hope that maybe the
writer was mistaken about th solar
piexus neing the brain of the soul, hut
further on we found that ouija himself
had told her "The solar plexus is the
spiritual brain." With this Inside in
formation and a warning that to get
best results you must think high
thoughts we invited "little weegee" to
the interview.
For the property of a higher thought
sort of person this ouija board certainly
had a remarkable line of lalk and in
teresting opinions. It told us that
there would b? a big war in 198;;, that
ouija meant spirits, and' it advised us
to "forget it" when we politely Inquired
If It had a message for us.
After a rest it condescended to tell
i us that Aunt Harriet, who died some
years ago, Is very happy, but vthen we
asked for Dumas to come and tell Us
i who was the man in the iron mask, it
wouldn't write anything except, "They
(ion 1 answer,
Wh. n ve returned the board we com.
, ni,-i,l.,l An thr, ,,',., fli,,,,'ir,l ,
ii , ,.m,.i in hoe., "Well" uia n,., ..i.i
Inriv
1 never tried this board myself.
H s the maid's board
Having t
decided to find out something about
his life history. The messenger at the
patent office was frankly amused at our
mission.
I ' VVeejah?" he repeated with a huge
grin. "Yassuh. Try de toy division,
Isuh."
The toy 'division was also moved to
1 laughter over the password, but soon
recovered sufficiently for a pleasant
I young patent examiner to gel out a
; col. ecilon ol the patent.
here are aout ,i" or in patent
"" ni ..i . ,
'"wntors. mostly toy makers. The
0U'Jn hoard and siniila Invention can
M1 patented in tiw United States oftly
as b toy The patent office does not In.
: fltilfe hit,, uny mystic ssnpertle. and
I1' doea not permit Inventor to claim
or describe such properties in their
. .. . .. . m
on, 'in miners.
In England, however, inventors' often
go into detail to explain the supernor
mal power of such devices. Thus, one
ltritlsh patentee Inserts the following on
his patent:
"If the persons or persons are of a
temperament suitable for the reception
of spiritualistic or telepathic messages,
sentences may be spelled out obtained
from such sources and possibly convey
i ,,r,-i,i,lnn unknown to ihe oner
atom the Urger iUmbe of messages.
1,,,-, , r. Biitnmnlt,' i.e. conlTimni-
ENDANGERING
Your precious
Young upe Just
To Hwe a couple
LM)Y FfciENDS
WORRY OVER
Cwrlfkl N. Y. Trrt,. !..
This seems plausible, if we discount
ouija s own statements that its name
signifies "The Master's Hand," or "The
?r.p ior ,nt it is Hawaiian for
iruth. If ouija had not told so many
people such different names for itseif
it might be easier to believe that the
word savors of the occult. As it is
we fear that some proaaic toy maker!
French perhaps, or German, accidental
ly put these two syllables together and
found the effect pleasing, so that he
named the board which answered yes
and no, ouija. a union of languages not
offensive to anyone in those days.
The ouija board most used in the
Lnited States was patented bv William
l'uld. a Baltimore toy manufacturer.
Mr. Iuld invented his board simply as
a game of the puzzle or mystic variety
He is very careful to say that he does
not claim any remarkable powers for
his invention, but, on the other hand,
he tells the public that he does not him
self know exactly what makes the little
table move in so uncanny a fashion.
Ibis Solomon-like verdict is the onlv
safe one for the inventor, for to deny
outspokenly that his li -tie board held
any kinship with spirits would greatly
injure the trade in his best seller, while
If he claimed mysterious powers In
league with the bits of wood, then he
might lie held responsible for some of
little ouija's playful jokes.
Take the recent case of the woman
who was unable to account for the dis
appearance of n sum of monev. Ouija
told her that a certain neighbor had
taken it, and this startling advice was
accepted as a clue from heaven. The
neighbor was dramatically accused of
theft, and the case went to court, one
woman claiming a charge of theft, and
the other after g libel suit. In such an
Instance the inventor of ouija is safe
from attack as the cause of it all, as
he never claimed that his invention was
infallible.
Most of ouija's history has been com
edy, so far, and a good deal has been
farce, but in a few cases an unac
countable force Is said to have guided
the board. The outstanding example
of this is the well-known story of Pa
tience Worth, who sent messages to a
St. Louis woman through a ouija board.
The mystery of Patience was that she
talked in the language of seventeenth
century England, using words and fig
ures of speech which the medium could
not possibly know, but which were al
most always found in dictionaries of
archaic English. Patience1 is still a
mystery a seventeenth century Eng
lish Spinster who came to St. Douis
to give her poems to the twentieth cen
tury, and for social chats with the
medium and her friends, all through the
ouija board.
We had talked to the ouija board,
and delved Into Its history, and there
was one more thing we wanted to know
about ouija how does It work, anyway.
We called up the bureau of standards,
the government's scientific laboratory.
The chief clerk answered, after his sec
retary had gurgled our message to him
between fits of giggles, easily heard
over the phone. The chief clerk was
amused, too, but the third command
ment of the government is Io give a
serious answer to Inquiries,
"Of course." he said, "we have never
made a study of this matter. Unofficial
ly, 1 should say that there U a ten
dency for the eye to guide the little
table toward some letter. The influ
ence of the eye is shown in that it is
almost impossible to get any results
blindfolded.
"Yes." he concluded, "it is probably
1 1! working of ihe rvbeonMclotu at(Mt.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 8-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85047611/1920-06-25/ed-1/seq-11/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document n-->
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 9-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87062237/1920-03-12/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>At the moment
that th » Ouiia board, which some years
ago excited the country and then virtually
disappeared, has again come into the limc
light throughout the world two brothers
Rr „ engaged in litigation hero over the
ownership of the patent,
The trial is now in progress of the suit
D f i 8aao Kuld, trading as the Southern
Toy Co., who is asking for an injunction
to restrain his brother, William Fuld. from
deriving pecuniary profits through the
*ale of the Ouija board,
The plaintiff asserts that in 1904 he
originated, manufactured and placed upon
the market the board under the copyright
name of the Oracle and that later William
K U K| started the manufacture of the
Ouija board.
William Fuld asserts that he and Isaao
p u ld wore in business together years ago
and that the Ouija hoard is tjh« original
talking Imard and claims that'the Oracle
talking board manufactured by Isaac
Fold is a copy of the one placed on the
market by him.
The Fuld« about 28 years ago were m
charge of a wooden toy factory known as
the Kennard Manufacturing Co* and the
Ouiia hoard was one of t! o devils they
made to entertain the young. It quickly
W on tremendous popularity and so over
shadowed the business of the concern that
the plant was largely*devoted to the
making of the Ouija board,
\\ illmrn said today that last year the
hoards turned out wore distributed
throughout the Foiled States and Canada.
4 Ran and William Box, brothers, living
at Molva, a small town, five mile« south
of Branson.
CAN THE OUIJA BOARD
NAME ITSOWN INVENTOR
Baltimore Brothers Qo to Court
to Oct Information on Ques
tion Answered. </text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 10-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063381/1920-11-12/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>/https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-ping-pong-craze</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1900-12-23/ed-1/seq-29/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1902-01-05/ed-1/seq-26/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>AN ABSORBING HEW INDOOR GAITS
WHICH HAS ATTAINED GREAT
POPULARITY IN LONDON;
The three men who occupied the studio flat
were having their quiet end-afternoon srnoks
together. There was the artist, w hose hair haj
turned gray after long years of painting an*
black and white doings; the youth who, fcesi
from art school, was just making a start, and
the man of business, who was the saving clause
of the combination. He put up the money wh»3
black and whites would not sell and the youths
checks from home were delayed In the mails.
I wish people would find something new wia
which to entertain us,  said the man of buij.
ness, in a bored tone.
New Year is coming, chirped the youth, aa
obvious statement, setir.g that Christmas «xj
just one day past. Perhaps Santa Claus tLpgti
off the dear girls to a new game.
There*! nothing new under the sun. Billy*
said the •Id artist. If taert was Id draw it jj
■ hurry.
Then there came a knock on the door, and a
messenger appeared with a dainty note. Billy
grasped it hastily. Billy was in love.
Its addressed to all of us, he said, with di*.
appointment.
All the more reason you should hurry up aaj
lead it, commanded the man of business.
Its from Harriet, he murmured, as he read
it to himself.
Head out loud, uli>.t commanded one of the
older men.
 Wont you ccme up to-morrow night and
play ping-pong.  read Billy. Now, what is
ping-pong?
Search me? remarked the one who was nut
artistic, except when it came to making money.
Sounds Chinese, said the artist.
Ive heard of pom-pom,  remarked BiUy.
Thats a sort of big gun which makes a funny
noise. Billy had ence had the idea of beeoininj
a military man. But ping-pon^r— thats a new
one on me.
Some new style of bridge. I suppose. mut
tered the artist. Its not for me. Ive sacri
ficed enough on that altar.
Well. Im going up to play ping-pong, an
nounced the youth. I dont care what it is, tit
names new. Better come along. Jack. You
were growling a minute ago about there being
nothing new, and here you are.
Dilly went to Harriets and played ping-pong,
and when he had not retumeO by midnight th«
other fellows knew that he was enjoying it. H«
would not tell them what the new game was
when he finally put in an appearance, but ad
vised them to find out for themselves.
An indoor edition of tennis is ping-pong, til*
name coming from the curious sound which tie
parchment rackets give forth when they striis
the little balls. It is played on the dining room
taMe, across the centre of which a low net is
stretched. Th> rules are almost the same as
in tennis, and the points are counted tennis
fashion. There is even mure chance for skilful
handling of the ball than In outduor game*
and there are tricks innumerable which add
interest and variety. Skilful players can ii??
up the volleying process until interest reaches
fever pitch. It is almost as exciting for tie
spectators as for the players, which U core
than can be said of tennis.
It is an absorbing game, as the EngHsh S«l
tell you. It his been played i:i London ilisisj
romis for the last two or three years; but ha
never been strictly in vogue until this winter
The ollieers of the British army carried pir.g
peng sets to South Africa with t.u-m. and have .
set up their tab) on tho wldt when the Ecea
let them remain Ln camp long enough.
Why the game has not taken hold in tiia •
country is something which Americans who live
In London cannot understand. They have writ
ten home about the beauties and delisht3 o! v
ping-pong. They laud it to the skies for tie
exercise it affords to busy c.tn who have o
work in offices all day. and to women who **
occupied with a round of teas a^d recepucsi
PING-PONG.
Continued on Seventh Iagc*</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86071197/1902-03-02/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn90059523/1902-04-06/ed-1/seq-23/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>From present indications society will
no longer be divided upon the lines of
birth, li ceding or wealth, but the quail-
Jiciition for membership in the innermost
circle will m- ability to play ping pong,
that fascinating parlor game that has
recently come over the seas to us from
aristocratic London.
Age. sex. color or previous condition
inaki no difference with the devotees of
the game and in England duchesses have
been known to struggle for the honor of
having a champion ping pong player from
some suburb at their receptions. Success
ful authors, artists and actors are no
longer being: lionized and made to roar
for the benefit of society. Their place ,s
but secondary now to the man who can
make the highest score with the bellum
covered racquet* and the celluloid balls.
The craze has but just struck the West,
although in New York, and. in fact, in
all of the Eastern cities, it is raging al
most as widely as it does in England.
The dealers say they are unable to keep
up with the demand for the game and
that thousands of sets have been sold,
v.ith the demand still increasing. Pins
pong parties are taking the place of
bridge whist and cinch contests and even
of bowline tournaments. No longer does
the Western swain sit contentedly in the
parlor with the girl of his heart, discuss
ing the weather undisturbed by the other
members of the family. Now the parlor
is in use. Father and mother and the
neighbors are serving and returning
and calling love 15, love 30, deuce ad
vantage, etc.
iiiiK pong is Bimply modified tennis
played upon a ta-ble in the houft« instead
of a court in the open air and is, in fact,
table tennis. Bui when the little celluloid
ball strikes the hard surface of a table
the contact prodapes a sound best
d< scribed by the word ping and as it
bounds against the viium racquet the
Bound pong, a full note lower, issues.
Some person with a quick ear and a
quicker imagination translated these
sounds and the gamfe was christened with
the catchy name ping pong, a name
tnat has helped to call attention to it. 
(i removed the part about the game itself)
Some of the tables are col
lapsible, with folding supports, and may
be stowed in small space. The bats or
racquets are already acquiring as great
variety as golf clubs. There are already
tournament bats, club bats and other
kinds. The best have vellum drums, al
though drums are also made in parch
ment and wood. Good players prefer the
short-handled bats to those of regulation
length. Ping pong- balls are largely im
ported, although American manufactur
ers are experimenting with various mate
rials in hope of improving the celluloid
spheres now in use, giving the regula
tion s|ze and weight. The net is usually
hand-made, of from five to seven inches
In height, linen bound, with a fair de
gree of elasticity. The poles on which it
is stretched are shapely wooden pegs,
with leather bottoms, which protect the
table, to which they are fastened with
clamps. In each outfit there are usually
a half dozen bats or battledores and one
dozen balls. Whether the game Is to
have permanent place among the amuse
ments is a question that i< being discuss
ed by those who have watched and ana.
lyzed the rise and fall of fads in the way
of indoor and outdoor amusements. Its
champions_ contend that it has every pos
sible requisite for the proper exercise of
body and mind that young women who
are noj equal to the roughing and phys
ical strain entailf-d by golf, tennis and
kindred strenuous sports will be heartily
and healthfully benefited by ping pong.
Others contend that the craze now
sweeping over Europe and America Is
but a passing fancy that will be rh<>-te>
lived than the bicycle vogue, and that
the new amusement will die out with the
coming of the outdoor reason, and tb^f
ore another w'nter arrives its hold win
have been broken and the devotees of
other pleasures will return to their old
gods and idols. </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82016357/1902-05-03/ed-1/seq-7/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>P1NGPONO IS A CRAZE GRAZEHAS CRAZEHAS CRAZEHAS
HAS INVADED ALL SORTS OF PLACES PLACESFROM PLACESI PLACESFROM
FROM CLUBS TO HOTELS HOTELSOne HOTELSOne HOTELSOne
I
One Factory U I Timilnjr TlIrnln Out n Tl TIu Tlrogand TlrogandSets < unand unandScti jflnll jflnllSet
Sets Set n l DnyTho Lay > nj Tho 1ainlon l 1assinn lon For fie Sport StiortHas SOItIInOrown SportIIas
Has IInOrown Grown Up Siicldtnlj 6llItltenlllo Ilc urcsrj ureerue ureerueLnnJunlo uroalueLanguage ue ueLanguage >
Language For Carne Term TermIn TennIn TermsIn
In the past few days persons walk walking walkIng walkIng ¬
ing through the quiet uptown streets streetshave streetshave streetshave
have remarked about the number of ofhouses ofhouses ofhouses
houses through whose open windows windowscame windowscame windowscame
came the staccato pins pln 1 pong pongl ot the thexylonite thexylonlte thexylonlte
xylonlte table tennis ball Accordlug Accord AccordIng According
Ing to the stories which aro told by bydealers bytJealers bydealers
dealers In sporting goods thousandsotsets thousands thousandsof
of otsets sets of this game hare ha e been sold to tofamilies totam tofamilies
families tam Illes in the city and the demand demandappears tJemantJappears demandappears
appears to be increasing One taco factory tacotory fuetory ¬
tory at Ohlcopee Falls alone is turn turnlug turn turning turnIng ¬
ing out 1000 sets dolly and Is far t l be behind bebind behind ¬
hind Its orders Pingpong Ptng poug outfits arc arcgoing arcgoing aregoing
going iu numbers now to suburban suburbangolf sulmrbangolf suburbangolf
golf clubs It shows what a bold the thesport thesport thesport
sport has taken on Its devotees that thateven tlUltoen thateven
even the golfing enthusiast must take takehis takehis takehlsping
his hlsping pingpong pIngp pnng ng to flu iinks links with him himOur hImOur himOur
Our greatest demand for complete completesets completesets completesets
sets including the regulation tables tableshas tableshas tableshas
has of course come from the clubs clubssaid clubssnld clubssaid
said a dealer yesterday But the thewomen thcwomcn thewomen
women women and children hare got the thefever thetever thefever
fever as bad ba as their brothers and andfathers andtathers andfathers
fathers If youre writing about the thepingpong theplngl1011g theping
pingpong ping pong craze you cant make it t too toostrong oo oostrong oostrong
strong So far as I know we havent haventsold haventsold haventsold
sold a set to any old ladles la les home yet yetbut yetbut yetbut
but I dare are say the game will reach reachthem reachthem reachthem
them in time This craze beats any anything anything anything ¬
thing I ever heard of Our belief is isthat Isthat Isthat
that its only beginning Hot weather weathermay weathermay weathermay
may affect our sales somewhat but butwo butwe
wo look for an increased demand next nextfall nextfall nextfall
fall fallOur
Our indoor putting green In the theback theback theback
back of the th store has been occupied by bya bya
a pingpong ping poug table for several weeks weeksLfits weeksL weeksLets
Lets L ts of people who never saw the thegame thegame thegame
game come In here and watch a few fewsets fewsets fewsets
sets get fascinated by the play and nndcud riudend andend
end by buying racquets and balls anda and anda anda
a net to take home and set up on their theirdiningroom theIrdlnlngroom theirdining
diningroom dining room or billiard table Theres Theresa
a game going on here almost every everyhour ceryhOUl everyhour
hour of the day People cant seem to toget toget toget
get enough of IL ILThe It ItTho ItTho
Tho clubs have been and are still stilltlys stillt10 stilltl
tlys t10 tl > o stronghold of the craze although althoughthe nlthouhtho althoughthe
the newspapers have had more to say sayabout sayabout sayabout
about the play In brokers ofllces of lces and andon andon andon
on ocean steamers So sudden has been beenthe beenthe beenthe
the passion for the sport and so much muchroom muchroom muchrOonl
room does a regulation table take up upthat upthat upthat
that most of the clubs have had to togive togive togive
give up some other sport in whole or orIn 01In orin
In part for a time or else sacrifice sacrificepart sacrltleepart sacrificepart
part of their diningroom space No Nobody Nobody Nobody ¬
body seems to object however Even Eventho Erentho Eventhe
tho most sedate of club loungers al although nltbough although ¬
though he may begin by scoffing at atthe atthe atthe
the childs play ends in becoming becomingcither becomIngeither becomingeither
either an enthusiast entllUslastor or a disappointed disappointedbut lsappolnledbut
but persistent duffer dufferCollege dufferCollega dufferCollege
College clubs or other clubs fre frequented tree treequented frequented ¬
quented by younger men are the worst worstsufferers worstsufferers worstsufferers
sufferers from the pingpong ping pong malady maladyTho maladylo maladyI1he
I1he Tho lo Harvard 1 alvald Club early In Inthcwlutol Inthcwlutolput the winter winterput winterput
put up the little nets on its billiard billiardtables bllliardtables billiardtables
tables and billiards have scarcely
been played there since Members Memberspay Memberspay Iemberlpay
pay the same amount per hour for forplaying forplayIng forplaying
playing pingpong ping pong that they formerly formerlywere 1ormerl 1ormerlwero formerlywere
were cbnrgdtl for fortbe the use of the bit billiard bllliard bitHard ¬
liard tables The club has since set up upIn upIn upin
In addition a veal ping pingpong pong board boardThe boardThe boardThe
The Yale Club has four tables in one oneof oneot oneof
of the class diningrooms on the ninth ninthfloor ninthfioor ninthfloor
floor The Cornell University Club Clubgives Clubgives Clubgives
gives up half Its diningroom to the thopastime thepastime thepastime
pastime and the House UouseOommlttee UouseOommltteenow Committee Committeenow Committeenow
now talks of letting the whole apart apartment apattment apartment ¬
ment bo used for It so many of the themembers themembers themembers
members want to play and pingpong pingpongtables plngpongtables ping pong pongtables
tables can be used ns dining lnlnl tables if ifit ItIt ifit
it takes too long to make the change changeIn changeIn changeIn
In n Brooklyn Droold n athletic club the ping plugpongcrs pingpongers pingpongers
pongers have Invaded the the handball handballcourt handballcourt handballcourt
court Most of these resorts Ies rts have had hador hador hador
or are having pingpong ping pong tdurnamentsand tdurnaments tournamentsnnd
nnd clever players bare Jave been dowel developed deeloped doweloped ¬
oped in the course of a few weeks weeksBoardinghouses weeksBoardinghouses weeksBoardinghouses
Boardinghouses In all parts of town townhave townhave townhave
have been hard hit by the craze The Thelong ihelong Thelong
long table ta ble in the back parlor l > llor makes a agood agood agood
good pingpong pl ping gllong pong board and a till the young youngman youngman youngman
man In the hall bedroom two flights flightsup filghtsup flightsup
up takes delight In making the star starboarder starboatder starboarder
boarder look like thirty cents The Thelandladies Thelandladies rholandladIes
landladies are arc rc not enthusiastic overthe over overthe 001the
the game because when played In the theevening theevening theevening
evening it has a n tendency to develop developa developrobust
a robust appetite for late suppersThe suppers suppersThe suppersThe
The vernacular of tbo sport has not notyet notyet notyet
yet reached a l high degree of development develop development oelop11ent ¬
ment For the present as Is the case casewith casewltbany casewith
wltbany with any new game players make free freewith treewltb freewith
with words nnd phrases plll ses proper to toother toother toother
other branches of sport Expressions Expressionslike Expressionslike
like You dealt cm the last time timeThis timeThis timeThis
This cue Is rotten Off side are areheard areIleard areheard
heard around the board Picturesque Picturesquelanguage Plctulesquelanguage Picturesquelanguage
language of n different character is isalso Isnlso isalso
also common The elusive celluloid celluloidsphere celluloidsphere celluloidsphere
sphere is as conducive to profanity as nsthe asthe asthe
the guttn guttnpercha percha A well known lawn lawntennis lawntennis lawntennis
tennis player has n novelty in the way wayof wayof wayof
of pingpong ping pong profanity When he hemakes hemakes hemakes
makes a fault he shouts Fudge I or orGoodness 01Goollness oreGoodness
Goodness gracious He explains that thatho thatbo thatlie
ho learned the game by playing with wltl1his withbis withhis
his sisters and it Isnt worth cussln cusslnabout cusslnabout cussinabout
about anyway anywaNew New York Sun</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82016353/1902-05-11/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84020274/1902-05-18/ed-1/seq-46/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn90059523/1902-05-25/ed-1/seq-21/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>DAFT ON PING-PONG
Washington Entranced With
Game, Which Is Played
in Many Homes
'fcOOM OF TIGHT CORSET
f(Xew Diversion Has Phenotncnal
Hold on All Sort* and Condi-
tion*. From 9teM Senators
tv DudtliiiK Debutantes.
Special to The Globe.
■ WASHINGTON, D. C. May 21.—Mover
j lias the national capital been so com-
T-letely enslaved by the fascinations of a
game, indoor or outdoor, as it has fallen
; (under the seductive influence of the won
jdc-rful new game, which, having set , all
J l^ngland crazy, has come with- a power
' to] stride across the Atlantic to exercise
its potent influence upon our social life.
i As a prominent leader of Washington
I society remarked the other day, "Wash
ington has fairly gone ping-pong mad."
. Conversation in capital society has now
i foe-come impregnated with the peculiar
I terms of the new pastime. Where for
merly one would hear "social precedence"
' and "rising man," one now hears "clever
i (half volleyer" and "invincible striker
I out." '
"Love" and "advantage" as topics of
; social conversation have now a ping-pong
significance entirely foreign to their for
xtx-r meaning among the capital gossips.
The ping-pong party has entirely sup
planted the whist party arid the bridge
circle.
The peculiar ping-pong of the celluloid
; balls as they are beaten to and fro (from
■which the game derives its name) is now
to be heard j in every Washington home
from the palatial mansion of the fam
-1 ily of the men who shape the nation's.
I destiny on Pennsylvania avenue to the
• humble residence of the congressional
I bootblack in the eastern section of the
i city. Years are a matter of no consid
; ©ration among the devotees of the sport.
■ The mature matron whose nod or frown
I Oias settled one way or the other the so
cial aspirations of mar.v- a newcomer
.at the capital is as frequently to be seen
i exerting herself in a manner wonderful
to behold, to keep the little swiftly pass- j
ing celluloid ball from dropping on her
I side of the net, as is the beautiful bud
| ding debutante who, with flushed face,
eyes sparkling with enthusiasm- and ex
. citement. and bared arms wildly but
Withal skillfully circling the air, is a
cSaily testimonial to the aethestic features
of the game.
Strike* nil Classes.
. . Nor are the enthusiasts of the new
gam" to be found only among the fairer
sex, - Washington masculinity has given
itself to ping-pong with an abandon
,Nor ar^ the enthusiasts .of the now
which would furnish a profitable study to
the seeker- of pysehologieal phenomena.
Staid congressmen, dignified senators.
Learned members of the bench and bar
When they meet together nowadays dis
cuss not, the political significance of the
lim.s. but the latest-make of ping-pong
racquet.
This -may be regarded as gross exagger
ation. It is a potent fact, however, that
ping p has attained a surprising vogue
■among Washington's public men.
All the leading hotels and cafes are
hastening to open up ping-pong parlors
on their premises, so that their distin
guished patrons may indulge .to their
heart's content in the game. . •
Senator Maur.a. when asked the other'
■day whether he favored the. erection of aj
ping-pong parlor in the national capital,
l>uckercd up.his brow* and gave the mat
tor a few minutes' serious consideration
before discussing the idea with a smile.
Congressman Sulzer, when asked to ex
plain the tremendous hold that ping-pong
has taken upon members of the-house,
said that it is a wonderful game for~ex
erclse. and gives one a good hand to
sustain the handshaking proclivities of
the vast army of well meaning citizens
| who swoop down upon unwilling repre
sentatives of the people with all the re
lentless energy of the notorious New
Jersey musquito upon its helpless victim.
As may be supposed, the stores have
not been slow to take advantage of the
commercial possibilities of the craze. In
* -addition to the fact that some of the
larger dry goods emporiums are opening
up ping-pong saloons for the accommo
dation of their patrons, the new game
has an important bearing upon the latest
styles. The ping-pong waist is prom
inently- displayed in the shop windows,
find is a phenomenal seller; while the
new forms of neckwear for women and
men bear handsomely embroidered figure.*
■of ping-pong racquets and balls upon
their silken folds.
Doom of the Tight Corset.
One important reform the game prom,
ises to effect, which may render rational,
the development which has been lavished'
upon it by England and America and im
mortalize the new game as one of the
most valuable and beneficent reform fac
tors of the century.
Ping-pong may abolish the tight laced
■corset.
Ping-pong is essentially an informal
game to be played at the spur of the
moment, as the whim seizes. It is a
game to be introduced by the smiling
hostess after the last vestige of the din
"■ner has been cleared away and ti;o
white table cloth is removed to make
way for the ping-pong net. Consequently
as the rapid movement and freedom of
body S necessary to me ping-pong player
renders the corset impossible, the charm
ing diner out has either to leave off her
corsets when she dresses to attend a
modern dim party or run the risk of
having to stand against the wall in ail
the-prim symmetry of a corseted waist
and, watch the merry movements of her
more fortunate sisters who, with grace
fully swing forms, keep the merry cellu
loid ball ping-ponging across the table
at a lively pace to the intense admira
tion of the man with the racquet on th^
other side of the table and .every other
man In the room. v
This good may ping-pong do; bu other
„ wise what peculiar qualities has the same
to '-rive it phenomenal popularity? Strict
ly speaking it is nothing more or less
then a table adaptation of lawn tennis
and tennis, while possessing to an equal
and even greater degree the same physi
cal benefits and sporting fascinations of
its replica has never attained the vogue
which has been vouchsafed to ping-pong.
Played on Dining Table.
Ping-pong is played on an ordinary din-
Ing table and its only accessories are
posts tp hold the net, the net itself
vellum string or wood-racquets and cellu- ■
loid balls: The game is for two people
one standing on one end of the table,
the other opposite. The player who first
delivers the ball is called the server ■ The
Other the striker out. i The service is
strictly underhand and is delivered from
beyond the end of the table.
£ The: ball served must drop on the table
beyond the net and is then in piav. if
it dops into the net or off the table it
counts to the striker out
The server wins a stroke if the striker
out fails to return the service or ball in
play of the table.
The striker out wins a stroke If the
server fails to return the ball in play or
makes a foul in service.
On either player winning his first stroke
the score la 15. The second stroke brings
the score to 30; the third stroke is called
•40 and the fourth stroke wins a game
The player who wins the first six games
' -wins a set.- -
This is all there really is to the game
of ping-pong. Certainly it Is a skill de
manding and skill acquiring game. It
lias simplicity and cheapness to recom
mend it. It is far better from a hygenie
standpoint than a majority of parlor
prames and is an extremely socialble and
interesting pastime. It is. for these rea
. sons and its similarity to tennis, a game
calculated to prove attractive to the"
. younger members of both sexes. .
: But why It has set the people of two
' countries almost crazy: why old as well
as young-have taken up ping-pong when
they would not as much as look at an-
Our Opening of Summer fliilinery.
• Tomorrow, Monday, May 26th; V : sZt^Sgigie^
we will display the newest and . - ji^^^^^^^^s ■"-''
most distinctive styles of - mid- _ n£^^^^S| 3
summer Millinery. This showing jKjvaßJ^i Ir^k*
of the newest Parisian ideas at r*&l^p '
Mannheimers' simultaneously as , ' YL^SaEIfA
they are shown in Paris, London JmM^sfit\
and New York, will give you an •': ■•*/'_' FW?
idea cf how closely we are in touch ■" .-.' hjffi^^jiifch-^u? (m \'
with these noted designers. rf^^^^^^A^^
It also emphasizes the Prestige of '"^^jmtc^^^^^X^J
Our Hillinery Leadership. f '* '\if
You will see the very latest emerald if £g&^E&&t fetO^^
green effects in Paradise Birds, Plumes t^Jj£*%' ' *^ jhP^hP^ jK/'' \^
and Aigrettes (the new Paris vogue), CMfE|g^_/'' *%*£s Y^-§[
the Lilac Toques, the Carnation and 2^^^aoj^i"''" W'^j&^.'V^^'
Ameiican Beauty Trimmed Hats, all /fie^^^Ms *J> 4l^>^'X
the very latest. In fact it will be the ?^J&slgfi&yk& TT^"^- V/
season's most elaborate display of * y Dr^i-^af^. / IjJV/T^sijr ■■ -
High-grade Summer Millinery. "*ss??' ** as" Hmljr \*- /J/s
G3r*We cordially invite all. * *^fc*»'.MV&Gsn '</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1902-06-01/ed-1/seq-13/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84020274/1902-07-13/ed-1/seq-39/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1902-09-21/ed-1/seq-11/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 1-->
	<idhttps://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn99066033/1902-08-02/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 2-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1903-02-15/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 3-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88064676/1902-05-19/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>HAS INVADED AL L.R F PL AICES
FROM COLUBS TO -:'OIiS.
One Faetory is Turning Out a Wheopesdi
Sets a Day-Theaseeion For tileSport
Bas Grown Vp dadenly-yPItureanqube
Language For Game Terms.
In the past few days persons walk
ing through the quiet up-town streets
have remarked about the number of:
houses through whose open windows,
came the staccato "ping! pong!" of the
xylonite "table tennis" bal. ' Accord
ing to the stories which are told by
dealers in sporting goods, thousands'
of sets of this game have been sold to
families in the city, and the demand
appears to be increasing. One fac
tory at Chicopee Falls alone is turn
ing out 1000 sets daily, and is far be
hind its orders. Ping-pong outfits are
going in numbers now to suburban
golf clubs. It shows what a hold the
sport has taken on its devotees that
even the golfing enthusiast must take
his ping-pong to the links with him.
"Our greatest demand for complete
sets, including the regulation tables,
has, of course, come from the clubs,"
said a dealer yesterday. "But the
women and children have got the
fever as bad as their brothers and
fathers. If you're writing about the
ping-pong craze you can't make it too
strong. So far as I know we haven't
sold a set to any old ladies' home yet,
but I dare say the game will reach
them in time. This craze beats any
thing I ever heard of. Our belief is
that it's only beginning. Hot weather
may affect our sales -somewhat but
we look for an increased demand next
fail.
"Our indoor putting green in the
back of the store has been occupied by
a ping-pong table for several weeks.
Lots of people who never saw the
game come in here and watch a few
sets, get fascinated by the play and
end by buying racquets and balls and
a net to take home and set up on their
dining-room or billiard table. There's
a game going on here almost every
hour of the day. People can't seem to
get enough of it."
The clubs have been and are still
the stronghold of the craze, although
the newspapers have had more to say
about the play in brokers' offices and
on ocean steamers. So sudden has been
the passion for the sport, and so much
room does a regulation table take up
that most of the clubs have had to
give up some other sport, in whole or
in part, for a time, or else sacrifice
part of their dining-room space. No
body seems to object, however. Even
the most sedate of club loungers, al
though he may begin by scoffing at
the "child's play," ends in becoming
either an enthusiast or a disappointed
but persistent "duffer."
College clubs or other clubs fre
quented by younger men are the worst
sufferers from the ping-pong malady.
The Harvard Club, early in the winter.
put up the little nets on its billiard
tables, and billiards have scarcely
been played there since. Members
pay the same amount per hour for
playing ping-pong that they formerly
were charged for the use of the bil
liard tables. The club has since set up,
In addition, a real ping-pong board.
The Yale Club has four tables in one
of the class dining-rooms on the ninth
floor. The Cornell University Club
gives up half its dining-room to the
pastime, and the House Committee
now talks of letting the whole apart
ment be used for it, so many of the
members want to play; and ping-pong
tables can be used as dining tables, if
it takes too long to make the change.
In a Brooklyn athletic club the ping
pongers have invaded the handball
court. Most of these resorts have had
or are having ping-poug tournaments.
and clever players have been devel
oped in the course of a few weeks.
Boarding-houses in all parts of town
have been hard hit by the craze. The
long table in the back parlor makes a
good ping-pong board, and the young
man in the hall bed-room two flights
up takes delight in making the star
Iloarder look like thirty cents. The
landladies are( noi enthusiastic o\ver
the game. ih'[eeue vl'when played in the
evelling it litas :1 tLnuden-y to develop
a rolust i appe ,titel for int' suppers.
Th' ver naular of the splort has not
yet reached a high 'degree of develop
llelu. For tilthe present'I , as is thle ctse
with lally inew\ llnel. lallyers i]akee free
w\it'h woldtilis Ia I hI'tIll ise llroleor to
ither b)rt ch(; ot" 4orl. lxprtssion.s
"''hiii cl'11 is ititntll." "O') side" are
heard aroundl th lit iltard. Piecturestlue
Itlniguage ot" a dliflren'ollI il'lrt'cter' is
also coulon.I. 'ITh'te elusive ctelluloid
spiliere is aIs (Olldu(l(i'-ti 1o I)profaniity as
the gutta perlha. A well known lawn
tennis player has a noveclty ill the way
of ping-pong profanity. When he
makes a fault he shouts "Fudge!" or
"Goodness gracious!" He explains that
he learned. the game by playing with
his sisters, and it Isn't worth cussin'
about anyway.-New York Sun.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 4-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85053174/1904-11-16/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 5-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88085421/1907-10-18/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 6-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84020358/1902-01-10/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>PING-PONG.
An Absorbing New Indoor Game Which
Hns Attained Great Popularity in
London.
The three men who occupied the stu
dio flat were having their quiet end-afternoon
smoke together. There was
the artist, whose hair had turned gray
after long years of painting and black
and white doings; the youth who, fresh
from art school, was just making a
start, and the mm of business, who wan
the saving clause of the combination.
He put up the money when black and
whites would not .sell and. the youth's
cheeks from home were delayed In the
maile.
"I wish people would find something
new with which to entertain us," paid
the man of business, In a bored tone.
"New Year is coming," chirped the
youth, an obvious statement, seeing
that Christmas was just one day past.
"Perhaps Santa Claus 'tipped off' the
dear girls to a new game."
"There's nothing new under the sun,
Billy," said the old artist. "If there
was I'd draw it in a hurry."
Then there came a knock on the door,
and a mcs-icng-r apr''0" with a dain
ty note. Billy grasped it hastily. Billy
was in love.
"It's addressed to all of us," he said,
with disappointment.
"All the more reason you should
hurry up and read it," commanded the
man of business.
"It's from Harriet," he murmured, as
he read it to himself.
"Read out loud, idiot!" commanded
one of the older men.
" 'Won't you come up to-morrow
-ri,p i night and play ping-pong?' " read Bil-
tinique article Is doubtless the only
one of its kind ever made. Mr. Lew
Is alpo hns quite a collection of min
eral specimens, but has not given this j
subject as much attention aa some c I
ly. "Now, what is ping-pong?"
"Search me?" remarked the one who
was not artistic, except when It came
to making money.
''Sounds Chinese," said, th jHrtlst
"I've heard of 'pom-pom,' " remarked
Billy. "That's a sort of big gun which
makes a funny noise." Billy had trace
had the Idea of becoming a military
man. "But ping-pong that's a new
one on me."
"Some new style of bridge, I sup
pose," muttered the artist. "It'a not
for me. I've sacrificed enough on that
altar."
"eWll, I'm going up to play ping
pong," announced the youth. "I don't
care what it is, the name's new. Bet
ter come along, Jack. You were growl
ing a minute ago about there being
nothing new, and here you are."
Billy went to Harriet's and played
ping-pong, and when he had not re
turned by midnight the other fellows
knew that he was enjoying it. He
would not tell them what the new
game was when he finally put in an ap
pearance, but advised them to find nut
for themselves.
An Indoor edition of tennis Is ping
pong, the name coming from the curi
ous sound which the parchment rack
ets give forth when they strike the lit
tle balls. It is played on the dining
room table, across the center of which
n low net Is stretched. The rules are
almost the same as In tennis, and the
points are counted tennis fashion.
There Is even more chance for skilful
handling of the ball than in outdoor
games, and there are tricks' innumera
ble which add interest and variety.
Skilful players can keep up the vollty
lng process until interest reaches fever
pitch. It Is almost as exciting for the
spectators as for the players, which is
more than can he said of tennis.
It la an absorbing game, as the Eng
lish will tell you. It has been played
In London dining rooms for the last two
years, but has never been strictly in
vogue until this winter. The officers of
the British army carried ping-pong
sets to South Africa with them, and
have set up their tables, on the veldt
when the Boers let them remain In
camp long enough.
Why the game has not taken hold in
this country is something which Amer
icans who live in London cannot un
derstand. They have written home
about the beauties and delights of ping
pong. They laud it to the skies for the
exercise it affords to busy men who
have to work In offices all day, and to
women who are occupied with a round
of teas and receptions. Golf and polo
and outdoor tennis are very good In
their way, but they demand daylight
and fairly decent weather. Ping-pong
can be played on the coldest night in
winter or In the warmest summer
weather. Women adore the game, for
It is not strenuous enough to ruffle
them, nnd requires Just enough exer
cise to put a. flush on their cheeks. As
an after dinner game, they say, nothing
like It has ever been Invented. The
men may take off their coats, and in
half an hour the effect of the heaviest
sort of dinner Is worked off.
The implements of the game have
been on sale in the shops in this city
for some time. It Is usually called "ta
ble tennis," and that may be the reason
it has not been taken up. Americans
have heard of table games before, but
they had not the possibilities of ping
pong. In England they are already
wishing for "pit-pat-polo" and "krik-Krik-krickel,"
vviiiie we have not yet
learned "ping-pong tennis." Early in
December a ping-pong tournament was
held at the Royal Aquarium at Lon
don, in which several hundred men and
women participated for prizes. It at
tracted the attention of society, and
the game promises to be a feature of
future seasons. It is likely that other
girls besides Harriet receives ping-
pong outfits for Christmas, and unless
the English have told dreadful "sto
ries," people over here will soon be in
the midst of a ping-pong craze. New
York Tribune.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 7-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88053046/1902-04-10/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE PING-PONG CRAZE.
Baltimore Heai'ld.
Ping-pong, tho latest and most
absorbing a
great deal of interest among tho smart
set, in Baltimore, in nearly every large
club or fashionable residence tho game
of ping-pong rules the hour formerly
occupied by the banquet and the ball.
Neither the first night of a great
actress nor the opera excites one-half
as much interest as a ping-çong match.
Ping-pong, which is simply lawn
tennis adapted to a table, is sometimes
called whiff-whaff. It was played by
the Japanese years ago and is still be
ing played by tht
ping-pong was ni
and w
noise made by tho ball striking tho
vellum racket. It has been played in
rly every country. Tho United
States seems to be one of tho last to
no affected by tho ping-pong craze.
Home time ago the g
pong was manufactured by Kamley
Bros., High llolborn, London, Eng.,
and in a short while all England was
Every club and private
London lmd a game and, in
who could not play ping
looked at askance. Last
tas taken up
the Uni tea
fashionable game, i
?m. In fact, the name
rat started i
•easioned by the peculiar
Jap
of ping
house ii
fact, a per
pong
it
by the finest
States,
society i
nearly all of the smart set,
tho gi
Ping-pong has also found its way
into hundreds of less pretentious homes.
It may be well just here thoroughly to
descriho the game for the benefit of
those who do
playing
it know exactly what
Ping pong i
game for young and
old people. It has proved tho most
successful indoor game ever gotten out,
because it gives
of physical exertion and is free from
; the irksomeness of some of the other
social games that compel one to eit
agreeable amount
still all the time.
The game is played just as lawn tenis
table, and it requires a
great deal of skill. Tho usual meusurc
9 feet by 5 feet
is, «inly on
ments of tho table t
and W foot by 4 feet, but just
fur. may ho had
table,
inchei
lion
smaller
larger
The height of the net is o%
. The remainder of the game
consists of posts to hold tho net when
stretched across the table : vellum,
string or wood rackets, and celluloid
balls. Ping-pong rules are the same as
lawn tennis, with the few following
except'
In ping-pong only
serving, whereas in tennis two balls
are used. The ball must be hit upon
the first bound in ping-pong, and may
not be hit upon the alternative of a
tennis, upon the second
fly, as in tennis.
Ping-pong is for two players, but
able to play.
the rules of the game,
which everybody should know thor
oughly before attempting to play a
match :
1. —The game is for t.
They shall s'and one at
the table. Tho player who first de
livers the ball shall tie called tho
server, and the other the striker out.
2. At the end of tho first game tho
striker-out shall become tho server,
and the server shall become the striker
out, and
3. The service shall be strictly un
derhand and delivered from beyond the
end of the table.
4. Th«* ball
where
and is then i
the net
striker-out. There i
bnll is used i
fly. as
bounce
a largo table four
Here
vo players,
each end of
alternately.
•rved must, drop any
the table top beyond tho net,
play. If it drops into
off the table it counts to the
soond service.
in lawn tennis.
5. In se
touch tho
(5. If tho ball i
object abo
it bounces
fing, it is a let if the ball
passing over.
play strikes any
around tho table before
tho table top itself (not
post excepted) it counts against tho
player.
7. Tho server
stroke if the
striker-out fails to return tho service,
return the service
off the table.
8. Tho striker-out wins a stroke if
fault, or fails to
turn the ball in play,
ball in play s
table.
ball in play
the
return tho
that it falls off the
9. No
lleying is allowed ; but as
long as the ball touches tho table top
it is in play, and can be taken at half
volley.
10. On either player winning his first
stroke the score is called 15 for that
either player winning his
•cond stroke the score is called 30
either player win
ning his third stroke tho score is called
40 for that player, and the f«»urth
strok
for that player;
i»y
it her player is Rcored
for that player except
11. If both pi aye
strokes (40 i
deuce, and the
either p
that plAyer.
the next stroke he wins the game; if
he loses the next stroke the score i
called dette;», and
below,
have won three
is called
ga:
all i the hi'*
ext stroke w
-layer is scored advantage to
play
by
, until
either player wins tho two strokes im
mediately following the score of deuces,
when the game is scored for that player,
12. The player who first wi
games wins a s«*t.
13. The g.
points, 20 up.
case, change
five points scor
There i
ay also lie scored by
». Tho players, in this
the service after every
•d.likn overs at cricket,
great deal of science about
Xpert player of the
place n ball within
aimed at.
d ;
ping-pong,
inch
Ho can knock
8«
of tho pi;
the ball sideways at any degree,
that it will bo out of his opponent's
reach. In fa-t, he can • hat with the
racket with as much precision and
much certainty as if he simply placed
the ball then» with his hands.
Among the expert players will be
found ping-pong tables covered with
green felt and marked like a tennis
court, but this is not at all necessary,
— ordinary dining table will answer
. On«* thing well to re
member is always to see that tho table
a little to the side of the
that it will not c<
under the chandelier.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 8-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82016014/1902-04-26/ed-1/seq-11/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Ping Pong Craze
W .. - -(: '5 Vi L t-
tk "" . - .Jufl
How the Game of Ping Pong is Played.
Have you played ping pong? Xo; then you are not in style and what is more you are missing the new game which
is demanding the attention of people in ail walks and stages of life. It has invaded New York. Kven in the brokers'
offices en Wall street, it is said, there are ping- pong- tables where the game is played after business hours. The craze
ha? reached Topeka but it has not y?t developed into general usagre. Ping pong" is nothing- more nor less than table
tennis. It is the-yame of lawn tennis boiled, down from the out door vacant lot size to a dining room table. Those
who used to play tennis, and those wno played at battledore and shuttlecock years before that, will find many points
of interest in ping pong. The name sounds foolish, perhaps. Something1 about as bad as tiddiedewinks, some raav
think, but it isn't. There can be a deal of science and adeptness displayed in pin? peng Xot as much as in billiards
and more tha'n in pillow dex. In fact ping pong- is a good substitute for tennis on a rainv day. All that is required
for the gane is a table from 7 to 9 feet long and about half as wide. It is not should have a smooth, hard surface in
be any particular size, only sufficiently large to allow of good play. The table necessary that the table should
'rder that the balls will bounce. A net from 5 to T inches high is stretched across the table midway. The fame is
pliived by two persons, standing: one at each end of the table. The players alternate in serving, as in tenuis, only that
in ping pong but one service is allowed and- that must bo. by an underhand stroke and not hard. Volleying is not
allowed and the ball is only in play after it strikes the table. The count is the same as in tennis. So after all. ping
pong is nothing more or less than an edition de luxe of tennis. It is quite interesting and in many places has be
come so popular that tournaments and ping pong parties are held.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 9-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86086499/1902-08-23/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 10-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86091347/1902-05-30/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-theft-mona-lisa</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83016810/1910-08-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Da Vinci's "Mona Lisa," Missing
From Louvre Gallery.
Celebrated Painting Has Been
Mystery for Four Centuries
Savants Puzzled Ovor Beau
tiful Model's Smile.
Paris.The "Mona Lisa" of Leonar
do da Vinci, the world famous paint
ing for whVch an offer of $5,000,000 is
said to have been refused and which
is reported to have been stolen from
the Louvre in Paris, for 400 years
has been as much a riddle as the
Sphinx itself. But one manSolomon
Reinach, brother of the Reinach of
notoriety in the Dreyfus affairever
has been so brazen as to proclaim
the solution of the smile that
wreathes the face of the woman in
the picture. His answer was laughed
to scorn by art critics. Others have
commented on the painting, but Rei
nach alone authoritatively announced
that the mystery was ended.
The "Mona Lisa" for four centuries
has stoou a monument to French art.
For four years1501 to 1504Da
Vinci, friend of Francesco del Gio
condo of Florence, spent his spare
moments at work on the painting.
The model was Mona Lisa Gherardini,
third wife of Giocondo. According to
Reinach, the lovelike expression on
the face of the model is far from in
dicating love.
Reinach asserts that Da Vinci paint
ed the portrait gratis for his friend,
when she was in deep grief, to divert
her mind. He surrounded her with
musicians, singers and buffoons to
keep her in gentle gayety. He worked
at the painting only when a certain
expression appeared on his model's
face, brought about by a peculiar
strain of music. He bore no love for
her, nor she for him.
Reinach even went so far as to ex
plain the deep melancholy of Mona
Lisa. He declared that she was mar
ried in 1495 and until 1499 had no
children. Then came a daughter. A
death record of Florence, by which it
appears that Fanciulia, little daugh
ter of Francesco del Giocondo and his
wife, Mona Lisa, was buried from the
Church of Santa Maria Novella on
June 1, 1501, is cited by him.
Whether Reinach's explanation is
.true or not, it was not received read-
Da Vinci's "Mona Lisa."
ily by the French. It was known that
Da Vinci had sold the painting to his
patron, Francis I. of France, for 4,000
gold ecus shortly after its completion.
The king kept it locked Jealously in
his gilded room at Fontainebleau,
and upon the death of Francis I.
Louis XIV. had it hung in his bed
chamber at Versailles. Following his
demise it was transferred to the Salon
Carre, where it since had attracted
world-wide attention.
"What is she smiling at?" ever has
been the unsolved riddle. To artists
Mona Lisa's smile became In turn ob
viously saucy, sportive, flirtatious and
even naughty, while plain people
called her the "jocund one."
Taine discovered in the smile that
Mona Lisa had been at least flirting
with Leonardo da Vinci, flattering him
and railing against her husband.
Michelet, the historian, said that he
used to go to the portrait "in spite of
himself, as the bird goes to the
snake." Theophlle Gautier discovered
that the subject of the painting was
flirting with the whole world, "this
strange creature whose look promises
unknown joys and whose expression is
divinely ironic." "She smiles with
mocking voluptuousness on the thou
sands who admire her," was the com
ment of Arsene Houssaye, manager of
the Theater Francais, who saw "shin
ing from that smile only the soul of
Leonardo in love."
Walter Patter revealed to the world
that It was an encyclopedia. "In this
beauty," he said, "the soul appears
with all its affections. All the thoughts
and experiences of the world hav
left their traces on itthe animalism
of Greece, the lubricity of Rome, the
revery of the middle ages, the return
of paganism, the sins of the Borgias!"
And supplementing this, the illus
trious Italian Carotti declared: "She
is the emanation of the intellectual,
sentimental and poetic power of her
time, with all the mystery of the
human soul and all its destiny."
In Europe the painting also is called
"La Joconde" and "Gioconda" and in
art circles it is considered to rank
second in value only to the Sistine
Madonna by Raphael. Both are price
less.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87078082/1911-09-06/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE disappearance of the fa
mous "Mona Idsa" of Leonardo
da Vlncl from the Louvre, nt
Paris, Is tho latest nine days'
Wonder In the 'world of art. This great
painting, also known as "La Glo-j
condo," has been pronounced by many ,
tho finest in the world. It certainly I
stands In a list of tho world's half'
dozen greatest paintings and in popu
lar regard perhaps ranks second onlyi
to tho "Slstlnc Madonna" by Ilaphacl.
Some think "Tho Last Supper," also I
by Da Vinci, greater than "Mona j
Lisa," but this sort of comparison is
fruitless, as tho two paintings are
qulto different In subject and treat
ment Walter Pater pronounced "La
Giocondo" as "in tho truest sense
Leonardo's masterpiece."
The painting is a portrait of Ma
donna Lisa del Giocondo, third wife
of Francesco del Giocondo of Flor
ence, both of whom would have been
forgotten centuries ago but for the
genius of Leonardo. It is said that
tho painter worked at this master
piece four years and then pronounced
it unfinished. To keep tho haunting
smile on tho subject's face he had
music and jesters in tho studio. As
wo now know it the painting has lost
somo of tho exquisite lines and hues
it had on leaving Da Vinci's band,
since It has faded through the cen
turies and has been retouched. Yet
even in this imperfect state it has
charmed the world.
Leonardo da Vinci was born in 1452,
the natural son of a Florentine notary
and a peasant woman. He was cele
brated not only as a painter, but ns a
sculptor, architect, pngineer nnd scien
tist. He engaged in various engineer
ing and architectural works, divided
his timo between Milan, Venice and
.Florence nnd toward the end of his
life was attached to tho court of tho
king of France, where he died. Out
side of his many paintings ho did
much in sculpture, little of which sur
vives. Ho also accomplished mnny
works in the lino of engineering and
architecture, these being his chief vo
cations. In'sclence he was in advance
of his age, being especially versed in
anatomy. As an artist ho was a con
temporaryand in somo senses a com
petitorof Michelangelo and a teacher
of Ilaphacl, Fro Bartolommeo and oth
ers almost, as illustrious. His schools
at Milan, Florence and elsewhcro wero
tho beginning of n new era hi Italian
art. Ho was great not only as a pro
ducer, but as an lnspirer of others. By
many ho is regarded as tho most uni
versal genius of. tho renaissance period.
In person Leonardo was handsome,
with a fine face, great physical
strength nnd charm of manner. Among
his other accomplishments ho was a
musician. His "Mona Lisa" was paint
ed about 1505, when ho was more than
fifty years old. It was bought by tho
king of Franco and has since been tho
property of the French nation and in
more recent years tho pride and tho
greatest ornament of the Louvro,
where it has been admired by millions
from generation to generation.
Every one Is familiar with the paint
ing or with prints of it, Perhapa more
oopies, photographs, engravings nnd
other reproductions have been mado
of this than of any other painting' in
the world. Ono of tho proofs of its
quality is that tho artistic and popular
verdicts on it agree. Usually tho com
mon herd Is enraptured with things
that the art critics pronounce daubs,
and tho art critics aro enchanted with
somo impressionistic thing that is a
blank to tho man on tho street Dut
"Mona Lisa" is so supremely great
that it levels all ranks nnd compels
praiso from artist and layman alike.
The face, with its dowy eyes and
faint Bmlle, contains everything that
charms ua in womanhood. It is spir
itual, yet has touches of the "earth
earthy," alluring and still elevated and
sweet Tho charm Is one that oludes
analysis, as is the case with all that
is finest not only in painting, music
and poetry, but in nature. Tho effect
is wonderfully heightened by nn al
most weird background of rocks and
streams. This and the uphinxllko ex
pression of tho faco giva n 'mystical
element to tho picture that has per
haps proved its greatest charm. But
I am not enough of a highbrow in art
to trust myself to describe it and re
produce tho estimate of Walter Pater
In ono of tho finest pieces 6f writing
In English literature.
"Wo nil know," ho says, "tho face
and hands of tho figure, set in its mar
ble chair In that cirque, of fantastic
rocks, as in some faint light under
sea. Perhaps of all ancient pictures
timo has chilled it least"
Ho then goes on to descrlbo the
painting as n creation of tho artist's
train and soul rather than a por
trait of n flesh and blood person. Its
Infinite appeal is greater ' than could
have eomo from any physical likeness,
but rather arises from an indefinable
something not subject to decay, some
thing carrying a breath from the eter
nal country. To return to Pater;
The presence that thus roao so atraneety
bosldo the waters Is expressive ot what
In the ways of a thousand years men had
come to desire. Hera is the head upon
Tohlnh all "(hn nnrta of thj world are
-
come," nnd the eyelids are a little weary
It Is a beauty Vroiight out from within
upon the flesh, tho deposit, little cell hy
cell, of strange thoughts and fantastic
reveries and exquisite passions. Set t
for a moment beside ono of those while
Greek goddesses or beautiful 'women of
antiquity, and how would they bo troubled
by this beauty, Into which the soul with
all Its maladies has passedl All the
thoughts and ezperlenoe of the world have
etched and molded there. In that which
they havo of power to refine and make
oxpresttlve tho outward form, the animal
Ism of Greece, tho lust of Rome, the
reverie of tho middle ages, with Its spir
itual ambition and Imaginative loves, the
return of tho pagan world, the sins of the
Borglas.
Sho la older than tho rocks among which
she sits. Like the vampire, she has been
dead many times and learned the secrets
of the gravo, and has been a diver In deep
seas, and keeps their fallen day about
her, and trafficked for strange webs with
eastern merchants, and as Leda was the
mother of Helen of Troy, and as St. Anne
the mother of Mary, and all this has been
to her but as the sound of lyres and
flutes and Uvea only In the delicacy with
which it has molded tho changing linea
ments and tinged tho eyelids and the
hands.
The loss of this picture Is regarded
by tho French ns a national calamity.
To them It is not only priceless, but
a part of their very life. It has been re
ported, and Is probably true, that the
French government once refused an
offer of $5,000,000 for tho painting.
tlon of tno act. That goes, paradox ana
all.
An interesting fact In this connection
is that several months ago it was re
ported In tho public prints that "Mona
Lisa" had been stolen and a copy sub
stituted in its place. This wns after
word denied, but tho disappearance
now makes it seem a strange coinci
dence, almost a prophecy.
There is one other possible explana
tion. It Is notorious that in Europe
the trade of making fake "old mas
ters" flourishes apace, chiefly for the
purpose of gulling American million
aires. These copies are properly aged
by processes that the fakers know and
nro then sold for fabulous prices to
those who have more money than ex
pert knowledge or perhaps real appre
ciation of "old masters." To do this
work fakers have to ppssess originals
in order that the copy may be as
nearly pcrfoct ns possible. Sometimes
these imitations aro so close that they
fool even the experts.
Somo sucli an organization of fakers
may have taken tho "Mona Lisa" for
copying purposes,, expecting afterward
to return tho origlnnl or a clover du
plicate for n ransom. This would bo
so hazardous a game, however, that
even a league of criminals would
hardly run the risk.
Mnny pictures havo been stolen in
tho past but nono even approaching
the value of, "Mona Lisa." Tho most
famous case in modern times was the
theft of Gainsborough's famous por
trait of the "Duchess of Devonshire."
The "electioneering duchess" sho was
called, having been nctivo in her hus
band's political canvasses. This paint
ing was missing nearly a quarter of a
century and was finally returned
through tho instrumentality of tho lato
Pnt Sheedy, tho "square" gamblor.
Sheedy's version of the affair was that
the thief was Adam Worth, whom
Sheedy regarded as the greatest crimi
nal of the last century. Tho painting
was originally Btolen to bo used in an
Masculine Dross Hotorm.
The Men's Dress Reform society has
been foundsd in Berlin, with the ob
ject of briuglng.mnscullno nttlre to a
higher hygienic standard. Tho society
protests ngainst the "air tight armor
plating" of tho starched sulrtfront, tho
cost iron rule of black frock coats for
weddings and funerals nllkc and tho
general system of dress which Involves
tho wearing of many tight fitting gar
ments, each overlapping tho other.
The society is greatly in favor of knee
breeches for everyday wear in placo of
tho conventional trousers, which. Its
members declare, require great skill in
cutting and nro a source of considera
ble trouble to tho wearer. Stiff collars
and cuffs nro nlso taboo.
The Battle of New Orleans.
It has been proposed that the centen
nial of tho battle of Now Orleans,
Jnn. 8. 1815, should be celebrated In
grand stylo nnd that the United States
government as its contribution to the
undertaking should appropriate sulll-
Icient money .to build n magnificent
road for automobiles and other vehi
cles from Detroit on tho lakes, where
the Ignominious surrender of General
I Hull, with 10,000 United States troops,
made the most humiliating event in
I tho history of that war, to New Or
leans, where the only rcnl victory and
' glory for tho nntlonal nrms were won.
A King's Private Directory.
Great is the part which the humble
card index system plays in tho social
I life of King George of England. Peo
ple presented to him are invariably as
tonished nnd flattered to find that ho
knows all about them, their family
and their achievements, no puts some
klndlv nuestlon that shows intimate
THE "MONA LISA."
Upon its disappearance tho Louvro
was closed for several days, n large
force of police was sot to work search
ing every nook and cranny of tho
great building, and sixty detectives
were started working on tho outside.
Ono of the theories of tho authorities
was that tho thief was a young man
who wns known to hnve become enam
ored of tho painting nnd who had
visited it at intervals for several
months, sitting before it with a rapt
expression for hours together. They
believe that ho fell in lovo with the
face, ns painters have been known to
become enamored of their own works,
and grew lnsano upon the subject his
mania finally prompting tho crlmo.
So much wero people affected by this
masterpleoe that somo shed tears at
6ight of it Not a few letters havo
been received at the Louvro addressed
to "Mona Lisa" and expressing love
to her as to a living person.
That the deed was tho work of some
deranged person seems almost certain
for the reason that the plcturo could
not be disposed of - nnd boncq would bo
without value to the thief. A painting
is only valuable when shown. If tho
criminal could dlsposo of it to n pri
vate collector and t cannot 'bo con
ceived that any thief would dare to
offer it, fpr Bale or that any collector
would be bo foolish or depraved as to
buy it such collector would not dare
exhibit it for fear of detection. While
there are many copies of tho painting
that tho average man could hardly de
tect from tho original, thero aro al
ways those who can distinguish, and
now that the wholo world is on the
lookout for tho picture every copy will
bo subjected to closer inspection.
Moreover, an old, master- is chiefly val
uablo becauso it is an original,, and to
bo able to refer to it as such and to
know in his heart that the claim is
true constitute its chiof value to the
collector; hence insanity of ono form
or another Is the only rational explana-
effort toget one of Worth's accom
plices out of Jail. Tho mna escaped
on n technicality, however, and Worth
had tho plcturo on his bands. He did
not dare to sell It or even to mention
Its. existence. The painting was kept
in a hermetically scaled caso in the
false bottom of a trunk. The Pinker
tons, who were set to work on tho
case, believed that Worth was tho
thief, but could not prove it
This is where Sheedy came into tho
case. Worth had at one time done
Sheedy a kindness $2,000 worth of
kindness, to bo exact Pinkerton heard
of this and asked Sheedy that if ho
ever saw Worth again to find out about
tho Gainsborough. Som years later,
when Sheedy was running a gambling
Joint in Constantinople, ho received
word from Adam Worth, who was in
trouble, as usual. Sheedy, of course,
more than' mado good tho former loan
and got Worth out Ho then men
tioned the matter of the Gainsborough,
and Worth replied that ho was on tho
point of breaking tho ico on that sub
ject himself. Tho upshot of it all wns
that Sheedy acted as a .go-between,
got the picture out of tho false bottom
of' tho trunk where it was in storage
in Boston, bad the British owners over
to examine it, collected tho $25,000 re
ward, presumably turned over tho
money to Adam Worth nnd hla pals
and as a result of the incident got into
"art" himself.
Worth was so- grateful for Sheedy's
action in tho Gainsborough affair
that beforo his death bo insisted on
giving Pat an original Murillo which
had been stolen out of some monastery.
When this came into his hands Sheedy
tried to find tho rightful owners, ad
vertising extensively in South America
nnd elsewhere, but failed. Some years
later ho beard that Itolsull, the Moroc
can handlt, had In, his possession a
OorregglQ, which was also obtained.
'Pnt's reputation as a connoisseur In
high art was made.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn89066313/1912-05-23/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The "Mona Lisa" which hung for
five years in the Sajon Carre of the
Louvre in Paris, had suffered from I
the hands of the restorer; the red
ness of the lips and face had disap
peared, although the subtle smile and
wonderful hands were almost un
spoiled.
The British Government once of
fered 5 million dollars for the paint
ing, but it was not to be purchased.
The stories about the subject of the
portrait and the unending discus
sions as to the character shown
by the face and the meaning of the
smile have, apart from the painting's
undoubted value as a work of art.
made it a subject of universal interest.
On August 21, 1911, the picture
was missed from its place in the
Louvre. The guard thought the offi
cial photographer had taken it to
his studio to copy it. as he often did.
It was not until late Tuesday even
ing that the guard announced the
picture had been stolen. After a
hasty search, the heavy frame was
found under a stairway leading to
one of the cloakrooms. A scaffold
against the facade of the Louvre,
in i placed there in connection with the
[...] 
ch'efly to his use of oil colors' di
rectly on the wall, to neglect and to
the vandalism of monks and soldiers,
only a ruin of the grand original re
mains. He painted other pictures
during his stay in Milan but most of
them have been lost.
It was several years later, after he
returned to Florence that he paint
ed the portrait of "Mona Lisa," per
haps the moft celebrated portrait in
the world. She was the third wife
of the Florentine, Francesco del
Giocondo, whence the name "La
loconde" by which the picture is
known in France. Rumors of
Leonardo's infatuation for this
beautiful woman have never been
verified but several other sketches
and another painting were found of
which she evidently was the model.
He spent intervals of four years
painting "Mona Lisa." The sittings
were short because he
only when Mono smiled. The artist
is said to have employed musicians
and jesters to perform nearby in or-
easy to enter or leave the building.
A person acquainted with the inter
ior and provided with keys to the
various rooms could easily reach the
Salon Carre where the picture hung.
Some say the portrait was stolen
as an object lesson, to show how
careless the keepers of the Louvre
were and how easily pictures could
be stolen. Others think perhaps an
artist has stolen it and will return a
reproduction and keep the original,
or that a big reward will be demand
ed and at its payment the picture will
be returned in an indirect way after
the excitement has died down.
More romantic than any of these
conjectures is that "Mona, Lisa" is
another Helen of Troy. Some one
has fallen in love with her and in
desperation carried her off to his se
cret altar where he can worship her
away from the stare of the crowds
and jealously guard her from the
eyes of other worshipers.
Wherever "Mona Lisa" is hidden,
she is carefully guarded, for no trace
could paint' s en rouna! and Paris, as well as
inousanus or signtseers who nave
gazed upon her beauty, are still
wondering and talking of her disap
pearance. S. L.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88084272/1913-10-26/ed-1/seq-30/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1913-12-13/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>STOLE 'MONA LISA'
TO AVENGE ITALY
Italian Workingman Resented
Art Spoliation by the First
Napoleon.
ITS RETURN TO FRANCE
TO BE WITH CEREMONY
Art Dealer Through Whom Paint
ing Was Recovered May Get Re
ward of $48,000.
FLORENCE, Italy. December 13?The
authenticity o fthe "Moua Lisa" found
\ Hfirrrday in possesion of Vinccnio
i'erugia was. confirmed by experts
after further examination today.
The picture bears the seals of the
Louvre and other galleries in which it
has been hung; while the traces of re
pairs at the back of the canvas also
are visible. The prisoner was again
interrogated by the police authorities
this morning. He repeated his story
of having stolen the picture as an act
of patriotic vengeance for Napoleon's
depredations in Italy. He displayed
the utmost indignation at his treatment
by the police, declaring it unjust after
the risks he had run and the abnega
tion he had demonstrated out of pa
triotic sentiment.
A number of prominent Italians have
w ritten to the Italian minister of pub
lic instruction requesting him to per
mit "'Mona Lisa" to be placed on exhi
bition in Florence, its former home,
before returning it to the French gov
ernment.
Some weeks ago an Italian wrote to
Signor Geri. an antiquary of Florence,
saying: "I am in possession of the miss
ing 'Mona Lisa," but being a patriotic
Italian I desire that it shall remain in
Florence, the center of Ita'ian art."
He signed the letter "Leonard," and
the antiquary at first paid small atten
tion to it. thinking he had to do with a
madman. Later, however, he communi
cated with Dr. Poggi, director of the
Florentine museums, who suggested that
he continue the correspondence with the
man. This was done, and an appoint
ment was arranged whereby Geri was to
view the picture at Milan. The date set J
v.a- November I", but unforeseen circum
"tancea prevented the meeting.
Recognizes "Mona Lisa."
A young man fairly well dressed, visit
ed Geri Thursday. He said he was
"Leonard" and was staying at the Hotel
Tripoli. He asked Geri to go with him
to see the picture. The dealer notified
Dr. Poggi. who hastened to the hotel,
and on being shown the painting recog
ii'zed it as the genuine "Mona Lisa."
Dr. Poggi asked to be allowed to take
the picture with him. so that he might
ompare it with other works. He made
an appointment to meet "Leonard" yes
terday afternoon at the hotel, to agree
?ipoi the price. The director took with
him several officers, who placed the man
nnder arrest.
? On being interrogated the prisoner said
hi.- real name is Vincenzo Perugia, that
he was born in the province of Como,
Is b> profession a decorator, and is un
married. For six years he lived in
France, and for three years was em
ployed at the Louvre.
Perugia posed .?s a patriot. "I was
ashamed." lie said, "that for more than
a century no Italian had thought of
-.avenging the spoliation committed by
Frenchmen under Napoieon, when they
carried off from the Italian museums and
galleries pictures, statues and treasures
of all kinds by wagonloads. ancient
manuscripts by thousands, and gold by
sacks."
Storen Early in Morning'.
He had often observed, he said, in the
Louvre many works of art stolen from
Italy, and conceived the idea of return
ing to its true home Leonardo da Vinci's
masterpiece. He entered the Louvre
early hi the morning, detached the pic
ture. and removed the painting from the
frame. He concealed the frame under
the back stairs, where it was afterward
f-jund. lie hid the picture beneath his
Turkman's blouse, and succeeded in leav
rns the place without attracting sus
picion.
At the time of the theft Perugia was
not employed in the Louvre, but he knew
all the exits and entrances, and how to
avoid attention. He kept the painting
concealed, he said, until his patriotism
leti him to offer it to the Italian people.
The picture was identified by Dr. Cor
r. do Rieci, director general of the de
T'ai tment of fine arts, who was dispatcn
?J hurrit-dly t?> Florence from Rome by
t ie minister of public instruction, Luigi
Credaro.
Government Acts Promptly.
News of the discovery of "Mona Lisa"
spread in the chamber of deputies, in ses
sion at Rome, where extremist members
?? !-e engaged in fisticuffs in an endeavor
to prevent a vote on the election of a
nationalist deputy for Rome. The disor
ded ceased immediately. The deputies
surrounded the minister of public instruc
tion, who exhibited a telegram from Dr
l{,e*-'i confirming the statement he had
already made by telephone.
\11 laughed at tin defense of the thief.
Some of thein remarked that Napoleon's
?ieeds were too antiquated to constitute
grounds for feuds. If it were not so
Italy would quarrel with the whole world!
ils all countries had stolen masterpieces
from her, not excluding the United
States The famous Ascoli cope, stolen
from the cathedral at Ascoli. which was
returned by J. P. Morgan, was cited,
however, as an instance of American
generosity.
Senor Credaro announced that Italy
would apply the same generosity, as he
had immediately notified the French am
bassador, Camiile Barrere, of the dis
covery of the painting. He added:
Pomp to Mark Return.
'Mona Lisa' will be delivered to the j
ambassador with a solemnity worthy 1
Leonardo da Vinci and a spirit of hapi- j
ness worthy of 'Mona Lisa's* smile. Al- !
though the masterpiece is dear to all
Italians as one of the best productions
9f the genius of their ra<*e. we will wlll
mgly return it to its foster country, which
hat regretted its loss so bitterly, as a
fresh pl?dge of friendship and brother
hood between the two great Latin na
tions." ,
?Strangely enough, the painting is in an
almost perfect state of preservation, not
withstanding the vicissitudes It must have
undergone.
The French ambassador expressed his
thanks to the Italian premier, Signor Gio
itti: the foreign minister. Marquis dl San
Giuliano, and the minister of public in
*>tructon. Signor Credaro. for the notU
:t< ations he had received regarding de
tail.- of the recovery of the picture. He
aid that the French government and the
French people would feel the deepest
To Subscribers:
Subscribers to The Star
who are served by the route
boys will confer a favor by
promptly reporting to The
Star office, either in person,
by telephone or by mail, any
negligence on the part of the
route boys.
I
gratitude for the promptitude of the Ital
ian government and its generosity la de
siring to return the masterpiece to the
Ix>uvr?.
Finger Prints Confirm Confession.
PARIS, December 13.?Rene Viviani,
French minister of public instruction,
announced at the cabinet council today
that there was no doubt the picture
"Mona Lisa" had been recovered and w*
now at Florence, Italy. He said he had
telegraphed to the Italian premier thank
ing him and the Italian government for
their prompt action.
A representative of the line arts de
partment is on the way to Rome to bring
the picture back to Paris.
Fresh proof that "Mona Lisa ' was
taken from the Louvre by Vincenzo Pe
rugia was established today when his
dnser prints taken when he was con
victed some time ago of carrying tire
arms without a permit were compared
wKh those on the frame and glass of the
picture and found exactly similar. The
finger prints on the glass and frame
were preserved by the police and the
similarity with those of Perugia is ap
parent.
Excitement in Paris.
With ' Mona Lisa" found what was one
of the unfathomable mysteries has been
solved. The sensation caused by its re
covery was equaled only by that caused i
by its disappearance in August. 1011.
Special editions of the newspapers car
ried the news the length and breadth of
Paris, and last night it was the sole
topic of conversation.
The Florence dealer, Geri. it is believ
ed. will be entitled to claim rewards ,
amounting to IMO.OOO francs (JMH.000) of- |
fered by the Society of Friends of the j
Louvre and Paris newspapers.
Regarded as Priceless.
"Mona Lisa," or "La Joconde," is one
of the world's famous paintings, and re
garded as priceless. Leonardo da Vinci
took as his model for the picture Lisa
del Glocondo. a woman of Florence. He
worked on the picture for four years,
from lC*JO to 15?4.
It was bought for France by Francis I.
The value of the work can only be imag
ined since all offers to buy it were re
fused. among them one reported to have
been made by the British government of
$3,000,01)0.
The famous painting had hung in the
place of honor in the Louvre in a room
which was supposed to be always watch- j
ed. It disappeared on the morning of
August 22, 1911. and its absence was
not noticed by its guardians until some
hours later.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045396/1913-12-13/ed-1/seq-12/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>"MONA LISA" RECOVERED;
THIEF IS IN CUSTODY
(Continued from Pago
It to Its familiar place and guard It so
that thoft will bo Impossible,"
Tho Florentine-dealer, Gerl, It js be
lieved, will be entitled to claim rowardd
amounting to 240.000 francs (S-tS.000) of
fered by the Society of Friends of tho
Louvre, and a Paris newspaper.
Expelled Director Joyous,
M. J. Thomolele, who was director of
the Louvre when "Mona Lisa" waa
stolen, and who was suspended by tho
French cabinet because of the loss of the
painting, was overcomo with Joy when
he learned of Uk recovery.
Seymour do Riccl, nn eminent art critic
of Paris, declared his faith In the certifi
cation of Dr. Corrado Riccl at Florence
of tho authenticity of the "Mona Lisa."
"I do not think there is the sllghlesl
doubt." ho said, "that tho painting will
bo restored immediately to Franco.
"Italy has no claim whatever on the
'Mona Lisa.' which was given or sold tn
the French king, Francis I, by Leonardo
da Vinci himself."
M. Vivlanl, minister of public Instruc
tion, and M. Jacquler. undcr-secretnry for
beaux arts, wcro both highly elated over
tho auspicious event which ushers In
their term of office. The Italian govern
ment has advised them that It will de
liver over the plcturo at once and they
are considering the best and safest means
of convoying it back to the Louvro.
The French government will take the
earliest opportunity to express Its grati
tude to the Italian government for the
great service It has rendered in restoring
the lost treasure
Perugia resided near tho St Louis
hospital. He left here hurriedly on
Wednesday, saying he was obliged to go
to Italy on Important bunlncss. Ho Is
22 years of age. the son of a carpenter.
He came to Paris every year during the
season and earned about eight francs a
'day, returning to some village when work
was slack. Outside- of a few compatriots,
humble workers like himself, he was not
known to havo any friends in Paris.
A neighbor of Porugla described him
as an ordinary workman, having no spe
cial technical knowledge and completely
Ignorant In artistic matters. Tho neigh
bor, therofore, was astonished to hear
that Perugia was accused of stealing the
painting and believed that if the accusa
tion were true ho could only have been
acting at the Instigation of someono who
had exploited his patriotic sentiments.
It was possible, said tho man, that Peru
gia had worked at the Louvre, but neith
er his relatives nor frienda ever have
heard 1U
ITALY WILL RETURN
PICTURE TO FRANCE
FLORENCE, Italy, Deo. 12. "Mona
Lisa," Leonardo da Vlncl'B great paint
ing, which was stolon from tho Louvro
In Paris more than two years ago. has
been found. It Is now In the hands of
the Italian authorities and will be re
turned to France.
"Mona Lisa." or "La Glaconda," as It
Is more popularly known, the most
celebrated portrait of a woman over
painted, has boon the subjoct of ex
haustive search In all quarters of the
globo. Tho mystery of Its abstraction
from the Louvre, Its great intrinsic
value, and the strnngo fascination of the
smile of tho woman It portrayed LlEa
del Glacondo, wife of a rich Florentine
have combined to keep allvo Interest In
Us recovery.
Tho picture was recovered under
curious circumstances. An Italian wroto
to Slgnor Gerl, nn antiquary of Flor
ence, somo weelcs ago. saying:
"I am In possession of tho missing
'Mona Lisa.' but being a patriotic Italian,
I dcalro that It shall remain in Flor
ence, the center of Italian art."
He signed the letter "Leonard," and
the antiquary at first paid small atten
tion to It, thinking he had to do with a I
Later, however, he communi
cated with Dr. Poggl, director of the
Florentine museums, who suggested that
ho continue the correspondence with the
man. This was done and an appoint
ment was arranged whereby Gerl was
to view the picture at Milan. The dato
set was Novembor 17. but unforeseen
circumstances prevented the meotlng. A
young man. fairly well dressed, visited
Gerl yesterday. Ho said ho waa "Leon
ard" and was staying at the Hotel Trip
oli. He asked Gerl to go with him to
see the picture. The dealer notified Dr.
Poggl, who hastened to the hotel and
on being shown tho painting recognized
It as tho genuine "Mona Lisa."
Dr Poggl asked to be allowed to take
the picture with him so that ho might
compare It with other worke. He mado
an appointment to meet "Leonard" this
afternoon at tho hotel to agree upon tho
price. The director took with him sev
eral officers, who placed tho man under
arrest.
Passes as Patriot.
On bolng Interrogated tho prlsonor said
his real namo was Vlncenzo Perugia;
that he was, bom In the province of
Como, whs by profession a decorator and
unmarried. For six years he lived In
France and for throe years waa employed
nt the Louvre.
Perugia posed as a patriot. T was
ashamed," he said, "that for more than
a century no Italian had thought of
avenging tho spoliation committed by
Frenchmen under Napoleon, when they
carried off from the Italian museums and
galleries pictures, statues and treasures
of all kinds by wagon loads, ancient
manuscripts by thousands and gold by
sacks."
Me had often observed, he Bald, In tho
Louvro njany works of art stolen from
Italy, and conceived the Idea of return
ing to Its true homo Leonardo da Vinci's
manterploco. Ho entered the Louvro
early In tho morning, detached the pic
ture and removed the painting from the
frame. Ho concealed the frame undor
the back stairs, where It wns after
ward found. He hid tho plcturo beneath
his workman's bloiiBc and succeeded In
leaving the place without attracting sus
picion. At tho time of the theft Porugla was
not employed In the Louvre, but ho know
all tho exits and entrances and how to
avoid attention. Ho kopt tho paint
ing concealed, ho eald, until his patriot
ism led him to offer It to the Italian
people.
Riccl Takes Big Risk.
The painting has also been Identified
by Dr. Corrado Riccl, director general of
the department of fine arts, wlio was dis
patched hurriedly to Florence from Romo
by tho minister of public Instruction.
Lulgl Credaro. After a careful examina
tion, Dr. Riccl telephoned to the min
ister, who was incredulous. Riccl said:
"1 will stake my head."
To thin Senor Credaro replied:
"I do not caro for your head, but If
this news, after It Is published is found
not to be true, you will be dismissed."
Dr. Riccl answered:
"I will take full responsibility and am
willing to risk dismissal."
News of the discovery of tho "Mona
Lisa" spread In the chambor of deputies.
In session at Rome, where extremist
members were engaged In fisticuffs In
an endeavor to prevent a voto on the
election of a Nationalist deputy for
Romo. Tho disorder ceased Immediately.
Tho deputies surrounded tflo minister of
public Instruction, who oxhlblted a telo
gram from Dr. Riccl, confirming tho
statement he had already mado by tele
phone. All laughed at the defenso of tho thief.
Somo of them remarked that Napoleon's
docds were too antiquated to constitute
grounds for feuds. If it were not so
Italy would quarrel with the w1hole
world, ns all countries, Including the
United States, had stolon masterpieces
from her. Tho famous "Ascoll Cope,"
stolon from the cathedral at Ascoll,
which waH returned by J. Pierpont Mor
gan, was cited, however, as an lnstanco
of American- generosity.
Will Be Returned to France.
Slgnor Credaro announced that Italy
would apply tho same generosity. Ho
said he had Immediately notified the
French embassador, Camllle Barrere. of
tho discovery of tho painting. He added
" 'Mona Lisa' will be delivered to tho
embassador with a solemnity worthy
of Leonardo da Vlncl and a spirit of hap
plnesB worthy of 'Mona Lisa's' smile.
Although the masterpiece l3 dear to nil
Italians as one of the best productions
of tho genius of their race, we will will
ingly return it to its foster country,
which has regretted Its loss so bitterly,
MONA LISA MAKES
A ROMAN HOLIDAY
P.OMB, Dec. 12. All Romo rejoices at
the finding of "Mona Lisa." IClng Vic
tor Emmanuol was umong tho first to
be Informed. The news spread through
tho court and caused great gratification.
Tho papal secretary of state. Cardinal
Merry Del Val, convoyed tho Information
to Pope Plus, when he was making his
evening report. The pontiff said:
"I am very happy that such a priceless
treasure, after all, Is not lost to the
world, and to the French nation."
The French embassador expressed his
thanks to the Italian premier, Slgnor
Giollttl; tho foreign minister. Marquis di
San Glullano. and the minister of pub
lic Instruction, Senor Credoro, for the
notifications he had received regarding
details of tho discovery of the plcturo.
He said that the French government and
the French people would feel tho deep
est gratitude for the generosity of the
Italian government In desliinc to return
the masterpiece to the Louvre.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn99021999/1913-12-14/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>HOI PAINTINTWAS FOUND
"Mona List," Missing Two Yean,
it Recovered.
THIEF OFFERS TO SELL IT
Conceived of netnrnlner Mns-
Icrpleee to III True Home n -A
venire 'I.oollnsr t Na
tion ) Napoleon.
FLORENCE, Italy. Doc, U.-'Mona
Una," Leonardo Da Vlncl'a-irTeat.,-painting,
which was atoltn from tie Louvre
la Paris mora than two years ago, haa
been found. It Is now. In thirhands of
tho Italian authorities and wilt be re
turned to Franco.
"Mona Llsrf' or "La Incomati' as It Is
mono popularly known, the most cele
brated portrait of a worrian ever painted,
has been tho object of exhaustive search
In all quarters of the globe. The mystery
of Its abstraction from the Louvre, Its
great Intrinsic value and the strange
fascination of the smile of tho woman
It portrayed, Lisa Pel Olpcondc, tho
wife of a wealthy Florentine, have com
bined to keep alive Interest tn Its re'
cover.
Tho picture was recovered under cur
leu's circumstances. As Italian .wrote to
Blgnor Gerl, an antiquary of Florence,
seVcral weeks ago, saying:
"I am in possession of trie 'missing
Mona Lisa, but being a patrtotto Italian,
I desire that It shall remain In Florence,
the center of Italian art."
lie signed tho letter, "Leonard," and
the, antiquary at first paid small atten
tion to It, thinking he had' to do with
a- madman. Later, however, ne communi
cated with Dr. Poggl, director of the
Florentine Museum, who suggested that
he .continue the correspondence with the
en an. This was done and an appoint
ment waa arranged whereby Gerl was to
vlkw the picture at Milan. The date set
wda November 17, but unforeseen .circum
sty&CM prevented the meeting.
Kecejrnlscs Painting as Mona' Lis.
A, young man, fairly well dressed,
vlsHed Gerl yesterday, lie sold he was
Leonard," and was staying at the Hotel
TrKjqJL He aeked Gerl. to go with blm.
to see the picture. The dealer notified
Dr. Poggl, who hastened to the hotel
and on being shown the, painting, recog
nised It as the genuine "Mona Lisa."
Dr. Poggl asked to be allowed to tako
the picture with him so that he might
compare H with other works. He made
an appointment to meet "Leonard" this
afternoon at the hotel to agree upon the
price. The director took with him several
officer, who placed the man under ar
te t
On being interrogated the prisoner said
his real name Is Vlnocnid Foruala, that
he was born In the province of Como, I
by profession a decorator and Is unmar
ried For six yeara he lived n France
and for the three years was employed at
the Louvre.
Perugia posed as a patriot- "I wai
ashamed," ho said, "that for more than
a century no Italian had thought of
avenging the spoliation comwttted by
Frewefemen uSr Napoleon, when they
carried oit from tka Italian museums and
galleries, ptoturea,, statue rb4 treasure
ot all kinds by waajta l&W' ancient
manuscript by thousands ad gold by
Mens."
H had Ken observed he sM In the.
Louvre mmw works of art an from
Italy a4 conceived the Idea ot returning
to He tte home Leonardo Da Vinci's,
ma4nleca. He entered the Louvre
rarly In Hie morning, detached the picture
and removed the painting from the frame.
)lld? It tender HlHe.
He concealed the frame under the back
stairs, where li waa afterward found.
He Md the picture under the workman's
Mouse and succeeded In leaving the place
without attracting suspicion.
At the time pf the theft Pruia was
not employed in the Louvre, but he knew
aU the exits and entrances and how
to avoid attention. Ho kept the painting
cofkeaied, he sola', until his patriotism
ledblm W offer It to the Italian people.
The painting has also been Identified by
Dr. Corrado IUcei, director general of
the, department ot fine arts, who waa
dispatched hurriedly to Florence from
Hem by Ve minister ot puWla .lnttruo
tlec Lulsi Cretans. After a careful ex
amlnaetom Dr. Meet telephoned to the
miaJeter, wise was Incredulous, Rlccl
aid: "I wHl stake my head."
Te tkVs signer Credaro replied! "I
not ear for your head; but If this news.
At? HlHMt DoUr
Advised Peruna.
agSBHs&l&k k ''"wHl
nnvnnlninnK
BnSflgegegegegegej
L
vlvkotu m. Mcinc
Xafllccteel
Ta aTIt SYLVESTER X. BUITH
JVISSOS South. Grand Ave- St. Louis.
Ma, writes Peruna Is the beet
friend a sick man, can have.
"A few months ago I came here tn
a wretched condition. Exposure and
dampness had ruined my
had catarrhal affections i
of the bronchial tubes.:
and for a time there wu
a deubt M to my recovery.
"Wr good honest old doctor advised
M to take Peruna, which I did and
la snort time ray health began to
laisanve rery rapidly, the bronchial trou-W-e
gradually disappeared, and In three
Btecthe say health was fully restored.
"Janet a, grateful man's thanks for
his MateraUon to perfect health."
AjA Ymmr DrmcgUt fmr Vca Pinna
JUftay Asy Aimumae for 1914
after It Is published, Is found not to be
true, yml will be dismissed."
Dr. lUoot answered: "I will take fall
responsibility and 'am ready to risk dis
missal." News of the discovery of the "Mona
Lisa" Kprea.il In the Chamber of Deputies,
In session nt noma, where extremist
members were engaged In fisticuffs In an
endeavor to prevent a vote on the elec
tion ot a nationalist deputy. .
Disorder Onsen n't Once.
The disorder ceased Immediately. The
deputies surrounded the minister of pub
llo. Instruction, who exhibited a telegram
from Dr. Rice! confirming tho statement
he had' already made by telephone.
All laughed at the alleged motives of
the thief. t)no of them remarked that
Napoleon's deods were- too antiquated to
constitute grounds for feuds. It It were
not so Italy would quarrel with the whole
world, ns ell countries, Including tho
United States, had stolen masterpieces
from It. The famous "Ascoll Cope."
stolen from the cathedral at Ancoll, which
was returned by J. I'lerpotit Morgan, waa
cited, however, as an Instance of Ameri
can generosity.
Blgnor Cenero announced that Italy
would show the sumo generosity. He
said he had Immediately notified the
French ambassador, Camllle Barrere, of
the discovery of tho painting, Ho added:
" 'Mona Lisa will be delivered to tho am
bassador with a solemnity worthy Leon
ardo Da Vinci and a spirit of happiness
worthy of 'Mona Lisa's smllo. Although
the masterpiece Is dear to all Italians as
one of the best productions of the genius
of their race, wo will willingly return
It to Its foster country, which has re
gretted Its loss so bitterly, as a fresh
pledgo of friendship and brotherhood be
tween the two great Latin nations."
The painting Is In an almost perfect
state of preservation, nothwlthstandlng
the vicissitudes It must have undergone.
Perugia, although he has not made a
complete confession, hns admitted that he
concealed It under the falso bottom ot a
trunk, or fixed behind tho canras ot a
worthless sketch.
Sensation In Paris.
PATHS, Dec. li The sensation caused
by the recovery of "Mona Lisa" was only
equaled by that caused by Its disappear
ance tn August, 1811.
Special editions of the newspapers car
ried the- news -the length nd-breadth of
rarts and tonight It was the sole topic
of conversation. The finding ot "Mona
Lisa" had been so often announced, only
to be contradicted, that the news waa at
first received with skepticism, but Am
bassador Barrero's dispatch from Homo
to the French minister of publlo Instruc
tion, though brief, was explicit and the
names of tho eminent Italian experts
mentioned seemed a sufficient guarantee
that It wits the original painting.
Henry Marcel, director general of the
French National museum, for a moment
waa Inclined to doubt the news, saying!
'We have so ofton been cruelly
hoaxed that It (s only natural that we
should foel skeptical that the painting
has been found. The telegram which I
have read seems so clear and shows such
detailed knowledge, however, that It
seems to me the nows must be true this
time. In any case, tho theft .undoubtedly
was. the act of a madman. The motive
given 'to avenge thefts committed In
Italy by Napoleon' dearly shows this.
"It the experts' examination proves the.
picture to be authentic- we will restore It
to Its familiar place and guard It? so that
tbef, wll pe Impossible." A
i.fie nerwauae dealer, aen, it Is be
lieved. wlll.be entitled to claim rewards
Amounting to 2-W.060 franca ofr
fered by the Society of Friends,, of the
Louvre and Paris newspapers.
M, J. T, Homoiele, who was director
of the Lenvre when "Mona Lisa," waa
stolon and who was suspended by the
French cabinet because of the loss of the
painting, waa overcome with Joy when he
learned of Its recovery.
Seymeui de Rlocl, an eminent art critic
of Paris, declared hla faith In the certifi
cation ot Dr. Corrado Rlocl at Florence
pt the' authenticity ot the "Mona Lisa."
"X do not think there Is the slightest
doubt," he said, ''that the painting will
be Immediately restored to 'France.
"Italy has no claim whatever on the
Mona Lisa,' which was given or sold to
the French klnr. Francis I, by Leonardo
da Vlticl himself.
M. Vivian!, minister of publlo Instruc-
Uon, and 11. Jocquler, under secretary
for beaux arts, were both highly elated
over the auspicious event, which ushers
In their terms of office. The Italian
government haa advteed them that It will
deliver over the picture and they con
sidered the beet and eateet way of con
veying It back to the Louvre.
The French government will take the
earltst opportunity to express Its grati
tude to the ItaHan government for tne
son-toe it has rendered in recovering the
lost treasure.
Perusta resided near the St Louis hos
pital. He left here hurried on -Wednes
day, saying he was obliged to go to
Italy on Important business.
He la M yeara did, the son of a car
penter, He came to Paria every year
during the season and earned about eight
f ranees a day, returning to some village
when .work was slack, Outside of a few
compatriots, humble workers like him
self, he was not known to have friends
tn Paris.
A- neighbor of Perugia described him as
an ordinary workman, having no special
technical knowledge and completely
Ignorant tn artlstto matters. The neigh
bor therefore wax astonished to hear that
Perugia waa accused ot stealing the paint
ing and believed that If the accusation
were true he could .only have been act
ing at tho Instigation ot some one who
had exploited his patriotic sentiments.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn99021999/1914-02-15/ed-1/seq-20/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1914-03-20/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE RESTORED MONA LISA
By Frederic J. Haskin.
iL ?"More
rtpa^lv than the male." a WOm
an outraged England arid made all art
lovers weep by hacking the incomparable
Rokeby Venus. She did it to get the
vote. It recalls the most famous of all
art thefts?the stealing of the Mona Lisa
by an Italian to avenge the depreda ions
of Napoleon a century old. The complete
story of that famous mystery only
new may be told with authority.
Smiling the same inscrutable smile
which the master genius, Leonardo da
Vinci, imprisoned upon canvas 400 years
ago to the vexation of generations of interpreters,
Mona Lisa, mysterious portrait,,
restored to her admirers after
strangely vanishing under the eyes of h :r
guards and eluding the frantic search of
a nation of art lovers again looks down
from her place in the Louvre, Paris, the
interest of her subtle, mystic expression
enhanced by reason of her peculiar adventure.
Mona Lisa, or, as the Italians call her.
La G.aconda on account of the haunting
challenge which the artist divined in the
face of his sitter and which he wove into
the fabric of his colors, has enthralled
and fascinated beholders from the beginning.
Many explanatory pages have
been written on the meaning of this
famous painting, and. provoked by its
indefinable charm, its elusive suggestion,
many an art student has brought the
full power of his critical acumen to tne
task of finding suitab.e words for the
description or th3 picture's strange appeal.
Each attempt has failed and ea.h
writer has dwelt with peculiar emphas.s
upon the qualities of the Mona Lisan
smile.
*
* *
This masterpiece is one of the most
treasured of the Louvre collection. It
has been tentaPailltillg
One of tively valued at
__ , _ _ more than a milMnst
Treasured. r?. it
was begun by da Vinci about 1503,
when the master stood at the zenith of
his fame and power, and, accoiding to
v asari, it took four years of intermiton
t labor to complete. The woman in
hose likeness there was, or into which
.he artist wrought an intangible something.
cumpe ling, unres.ful, questionng,
in the mind of each who stared
ack at it, lived in Florence. She was
M,.na Lisa di Antonio Maria di Noldo
iherardini, a native of Naples, who was
narried in 1495 to Francesco di Bardemeo
di Zanobi del Giocondo, a
rominent citizen of Florence. When
she began her sittings for what has
since become one of the most renowned
of all the world's portraits she was
vobably twenty-five or younger Da
Vinci, painter, poet, engineer, philosopher
and mystic:, was fifty-one. Was
it an unusual woman that the ripened
master painted or was it a forceful
symbol coined by his rich, discerning
miml? Many times this quest-on has
:->cc-n put to. the lady of the superior
smile, answered only by the tantalizing
glance through the thick, protecting
varnish.
No wonder, when the loss of their
treasure was discovered on the morning
of August 21, 1911, a Monday, all Paris
was wrbught to a frenzy. The news of
the theft was received in all parts >f
the civilized world with the same feelnes
of dismay. The picture missing
i'rom its place in the Sa'on Carre was
the most beautiful from Leonardo's
brush, and one of the most precious
creations of western culture.
*
* *
Two years and four months passed by
without a trace of the vanished work.
All efforts of the
Two Years Pass French police re U7,?
ni_? malned fruitless.
Without a Clue. High rewards of,
fered for the return of the painting went
unclaimed, and every clue as to the
Illustration, and other papers,
? nothing more of the criminal was learned
j Llllustration immediately announced |
I that it would pay 40,000 francs, about
J $8,000, to any one who would return the !
! picture by September 26, and 45,000 francs
I ?or $9,000?if the picture was brought to
! them by September 1. It was further announced
that no questions would be
asked. The editors received some five
hundred letters in answer to their announcements,
investigated some one hundred
cases, and learned nothing. The
Museum Club (Amis du Louvre) gave the
police 25,000 francs to be used for the obtaining
of the painting.
The court of investigation convened August
22, and in its hearings the photographed
thumb print played a leading
role. No less than 257 persons were ordered
by the court to submit their thumb
prints for comparison. Among those furnishing
such prints were the directors of
r
| whereabouts of the thief ended just tl
j without the Louvre gates. As the months n
spied by while the endeavors of the police
proved vain and not even rumors came
of a Mona Lisa in foreign lands, all hope
that the picture would ever be recovered
was given up. It was concluded that _
the work had been destroyed. The fate *
of Mona Lisa was put to the account of
one of those unintelligible acts of vandalism
which go to swell the records of hu- ^
man pathology.
Boundless was the enthusiasm, then, K
which greeted the sudden, unexpected re- L
appearance of the Gioconda Thursday, ^
December 11, 1913, at Florence. In Flor- g(
ence the original Mona Lisa had sat for
a portrait by one of the greatest painters w
of all times, and in a dingy inn at Florence
the lost painting was found again. C(
The Italian authorities obtained imme- p;
diate possession of the picture, which h
was taken in triumphal procession a:
through Italy, under police guard to
Rome, to the French ambassador Bar- tl
rere. and, then, to Milan, where the di- w
rector general of the Louvre, Henry Mar- H
eel, and the director of paintings, Jd. Leprieur.
came to take charge if it. The b
Mona Lisa was again safely housed in in
Paris last New Year day, and was again
hung in its accustomed place at the n,
Louvre, which place had been filled dur- ee
ing the time of its loss by Raphaels p
Castiglione. L
The theft of this irreplaceable work tr
was an extraordinary one, in that the ol
criminal had been able to penetrate one to
of the best guarded treasure houses of E
f Europe and make away with one of its te
j most prized and precious possessions, and tr
i disappear with his loot without leaving ai
cl ouigio iiauc ucuiiiu. i no unci nao ?n ui
unusual one, in that for two years and tt
four months he kept his secret, the price- m
less Mona Lisa hidden away in his gar- p<
ret bedroom in Paris, only in the end to tt
fail into the hands of the criminal au- ai
thorities through an act of childish care- th
lessness, an almost Imbecile simplicity. ol
d(
* * te
Immediately, after the discovery of the ^
theft, It was thought in Paris that the ol
thief had hidden el
Print Of Thumb himself away in tj
Only Cine Left. *he galery Satur ?
J day afternoon, re ti
mained in the place all night, and es- **
caped with his spoil Monday morning. n|
The glass casing and the frame of the r<
picture were found leaning against the 17
wall of a narrow stairway leading from n
the galiery des sept metres, where the le
old Italian pictures are hung, to the a
Court of the Sphinx. The door opening S)
from the stairway part of glass protect- n
ed by iron work, was locked, and, at the
investigation, Sauvet, one of the working- f,
men in the Louvre, remembered having ^
opened the door at the request of a per- il
son upon whom he came sitting at the 51
bottom of the stairway. He failed to
take further notice of this person, other
! than that he was wearing a blouse simi;
!ar to those worn by the regular guards. c
I As Monday is cleaning day, and visitors a
are barred, no suspicion crossed his mind C
! but that the man was what he seemed o
! an official Here the trail ended. A print ?
j of a left thumb upon the abandoned
glass frame was all that remained in the j7
I n.'9 v r?f a pIuo tn tViu nolipe
he Louvre. The thief, of course, was 1
ot upon the list of those investigated. '
*
* *
Vincerizo Peruggia, an Italian, the real
espoiler, as established by his own confession
and the S
Italian Clears Up exact agreement
,r , , of Hie finger print
Murky Mystery. found upon the
lass case with that of his own thumb,
hen taken into custody by the Italian
olice cleared up the murky mystery,
[e maintained that he entered the ]
mirrn tmrothne n-!tl, nik/i. I 1
londay morning:, made his way unob- r
srved to the Mona Lisa, removed it c
om its hanging, carried it to the stair- c
ay where the frames were found, cut ^
le painting loose from its casing, con- g
jaled it in his blouse and persuaded a I
assing workman to open the door for
Im without so much as seeing a guard g
round. Once outside the Louvre, he pro;eded
to his lodging house, a nest for a 2
ilony of Italian workmen, where he hid t
le picture and went on with his regular a
ork?that of a house painter and glazier, .jIe
continued to ply his trade for more ,
lan two years, a thing worth to him a
emendous fortune concealed in the false 2
Dttom of his wooden trunk, before try- I
ig to dispose of it.
Only once was the suspicion of the po- B
ce directed upon him. But how he \
leaped that once is another mystery,
eruggia had been employed at the q
ouvre as a glazier and had been inusted
with the work of framing some f
' the most costly masterpieces. In Oc- t
>ber, 1911, Prof. Pierre Marcel of the t
cole des Beaux-Arts wrote an open let- a
r to the paper Figaro suggesting that t
ace of the criminal was to be sought a
nong the Louvre glaziers. The director f
' painting took the suggestion, obtained
ie names of those so employed and for- e
erly so employed, upon which list ap- f
3ared the name of Peruggia, who, with g
te rest, was subject to an examination
id a house search. The mystery is that c
ie police did not take the finger prints 1
I these men for comparison, as had been i
me at the first investigation. 1
Peruggia's downfall came with his at;mpt
to dispose of his spoil. He wrote
ovember 28, 1913, to Alfred Geri, owner
! the Galleria d'Arte e Moderna, at Florice,
a dealer in art works, offering, un- ^
er the name of Leonardi, to sell him
ie Mona Lisa, which he explained, as a
atriotic Ital.an, he felt ought to be relrned
to Italy, the land of its producon.
This plea, strengthened to one of (
atriotic bitterness that rich Pang should .
ot be decorated with the spoils of Italy,
3bbed during the times of Napoleon, he I
lalntained after his arrest. ' j
Geri sought counsel from Prof. Giovan- ^
i Poggi, director of the Florence galfries
As a result of his conference he ;
nswered the letter from Paris entering :
eartily into the writer's proposals and .
sn.iment, i.naily arranging a meeting in 1
taly, which took place at Flo.ence Deember
11, when the lost Mona Lisa was :
ra\sn from her hiding place under the
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85042303/1914-06-05/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Mona Lisa" Thief on Trial.
Florence. Italy, June 4. The trial
of Vincenzo Perugia, on the charge
of stealing Da Vinci's masterpiece,
"Mona Lisa" from the Douvre in Par
is, began here today.
The disappearance of the picture
on August 22, ll'll, caused a sensa
tion throughout the world, and search
for it was not successful until Decem
ber 12, lf'13, when Perugia offered it
for sale to a Florentine antiquarian.
D. It. Analili. an alienist, said at
todays' hearing that Perugia was only
partially responsible for his actions.
Perugia did not deny that he had
taken "Mona Lisa" from the Louvre.
He said it was his desire to have
i placed in the Palazza Delig Vffizi
in Florence. Ti stimony as to the
authenticity of the picture was given
by st-vral experts. Other witnesses
gave evidence as to the details of the
i tht It.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1914-06-06/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88084272/1919-02-08/ed-1/seq-20/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 1-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn91064011/1911-08-31/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 2-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1913-12-16/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CREDIT ITALIAN'S STORY
OF MONA LISA THEFT
Officials of Louvre in Paris Make
Experiments With
Dummy.
PARIS, December 10.?The police and
the officials of the Louvre give full cre
dence to Vincenzo Perugia's story of the
theft of the Mona Lisa, The authorities
have closely examined all the details and '
tind nothing to cast doubt on Perugia s
narrative.
Seymour de Rlccf, an art expert, de
scribed today the experiments made im
mediately after the Mona Lisa was stolen.
A dummy picture of the same size and
weight, from thirty-live to forty pounds,
with the frame, was easily removed by a
police official who had no experience in
handling pictures, and who carried it
twenty yards to the staircase, where the
frame was subsequently found. The op
eration required less than one minute. An
other official accustomed to transporting
pictures did the same thing In twenty
seconds.
It has been proved that Perugia had
assisted in rehanging the "Mona Lisa"
some time before the theft. The picture
without its frame is about twenty-one
inches wide by thirty high, and weighs
five pounds. The painting is on wood
less than an inch thick.
Marquis de Chennevieres. assistant
conservator of the Louvre, said today:
"One man could not alone have moved
the Mona Lisa. It would have taken
him too long."
Advances Motive for Theft.
FLORENCE, Italy. December 16.?
Signor Chlni, the Italian painter, writes
to a local paper today urging a theory
that the theft of the Mona Lisa was
"simulated, in order to conceal some
badly execufed restorations of the pic
ture." He states that he himself de
tected on the painting some retouches
of which there is no official record. He
thinks it would be Interesting to es
tablish whether all the restorations
now traceable existed before the pic
ture left the Louvre.
MILAN. Italy. December 16.?A num
ber of prominent citizens of Milan to
dav conveyed to Camille Barrere,
French ambassador to Italy, a request
that the 'Mona Lisa" be exhibited here.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 3-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1931-10-11/ed-1/seq-77/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 4-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88084272/1919-02-08/ed-1/seq-20/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 5-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn96091104/1911-12-01/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WOMAN'S SOUL
IS REFLECTED
MONA LISA THE SUBJECT OF AN
ADDRESS BY PREACHER.
Story of the Stolen Masterpiece Told
by Dp. J. Monroe Taber
In New York.
dral in life attitude of prayer, her
wonderful face uplifted before the
silent altar. The noble husband of
Mona Lisa came to the artist to ar
range for the painting. The consum
mate mark of her radiant beauty was
the soulful and radiant tenderness
of the smile which brok through
the sweet sadness of her face. For
years Leonardo studied that face at
intervals. He wrought upon the can-
GREAT SPEECH
OF MR. PADGET
HIS EFFORT AT NEW ORLEANS
- EVIDENTLY MADE A MOST
PROFOUND IMPISION.
"The world is" full of music if you
cau but hear Its throbbing vibrations
on every hand " declared the Rev. Dr. from the jlgate(j face 0f Mona Lisa
Congressman Padgett evidently
mAria A Croat cffrrt hafnra tha A marl.
vas until he had transferred to the AtaociitloQ at NeT7 0r.
leans, La. All who heard it make
that declaration. F. O. Watts, of
Nnahvilln whn rntlrsH tmm fha nraa.
At last, in the closing moments of nnn..ti fm
her brief life, the woman soul leaped preBldent Hutton Qf phoQlx N&.
enriched canvas all but the glory or
the smile. For this he waited and
watched.
J. Monroe Taber, pastor of Trinity tQ the goul of the painter and touched
Methodist Episcopal church, in b'lng
Ing the meaning of his sermon on hlg bruah and on the following day
"A $5,000,000 Smile;, the Story of th 'face of Mona Lisa shown forth
tional Bank, that Mr. Padgett's
aneach via one nf th pxPAtont uvcr
ith mlrsculou. .Mil and MderMSi fcj tBsockUolL
Special Ready-to-Wear Sale for Saturday,
Monday and All Next WeeK At
Mona Lisa," to his congregation last from the compieted painting. Al
nighL The preacher had used a3 an though tne great master felt that a
Illustration the description of a won- my8tlc something was still wanting
flerful organ in a cathedrial in a Eu- tQ make perfect his work, he never
ropean city, only a small sectin of theleSB confessed that he could do
Which was vibihle, while pipes giving no more
forth music, v ere placed throughout ..Witn fun appreciation of every in-i
the edifice. spired touch of the painter's genius,
"We see only here and there an . tha lit finish of hands and
lnstrument,a glimpse of beauty, a hint fQ-m of wondfcrfui beauty, the world
of melody," said he, "but music is ev- hag recognlze3 that the great charm CRIMP
rywhere." and yalue of the palntlng ia the
The Rev. Dr. taber was preaching Bmile-illuminated face of Mona Lisa. :
to an audience composed cnieny oi ,.Th aorrow 0f Mona Lisa, caused
by the death of her darling child, Is
transfigured by the glory of the sw
smile.
must be remembered that Mr. Watts
is a competent judge and also that the
association has in recent years heard
some of the ablest speakers of the
nation.
STUBBED TOE
BAR TO MARINES
PUT IN ASPIRATIONS OF
MEMPHIAN TO JOIN
FEDERAL FORCES
A Timely Event That Affords
Highly Interesting Values
Immensely Important
Sale of
SUITS, COATS
SKIMS & WAISTS
women, although a number of men
were present. Women acted as ush
ers, and when the time for the offer
ing came women passed around the
collection plates. This was because
of the pastor's desire to have a ser
vice for the women, the men having
had their share, he said, in the lo
cal campaign of the Men and Relig
ion Forward Movement.
The preacher brought home the
ralue of a smile, bringing cheerful
ness w here otherwise might be gloom
and unhappinoss. tils tneme was
drawn from the story of the 4Iona
Lisa from the time of Its conception
by Lenanio da Vinci to the date of
its tlieft from the Louvre Gallery in
Paris. A reproduction of the famous
masterpiece, illuminated by electric
lights, occupied a place in front of
the ros.r.im, lu full view of the con
gregation. .
Pointing to the picture before him
the preacher called attention to the j if
peculiar fact that for centuries the
mristers had been unable to reproduce
the smile of Mona Lisa, and that it
Id r ot even lie produced in photo
graphs of the criminal. The Rev. Dr.
Taber, before beginning his discourse,
read the fifty-third Psalm. In part
he said:
"The great Louvre Gallery Is In
ixiu.ti mug iui i.uc gicai muua iad.
Paris, Italy and a world of art loving
people stand in tadness oyer the trag
ic daring cf the theft of the master
piece. Groups bf marble statues
seem less aglow, and many an im
mortal picture' upon the breathing
canvas of the great masters beears
a lonesome look since Mona Lisa
went away.
"Mona Lisa, a patrician lady of rare
beauty, lived in Florence four centu
ries ago. Lensrdo da Vinci, sculptor,
phillosopher, mathematician, but first
of all, painter, Btood amid master
pieces produced during those years
when his rare genius made him im
mortal. Not satisfied with all this,
the painters supreme ambition was
to find the 'woman soul' and trans
figure with it the face and form of
his rarest masterpiece in canvas.
"God sent to him Mona Lisa. Le
onardo first saw her in a great cathe-
A dilapidated and swollen toe put
reet a crlmD and end to tne naval aspira
tions or a young Memphian, who ap
plied to the local marine recruiting
'Or, In this nrnrld nt -nnrrnw ROr-
kJV,, ... , -- ,U o..4.1.- - v. .
become most DLa"""' i'UULUe"' express ouua-
row and sadness may
beautiful if we may touch them with
the glory and radiance of a genuine
smile.
ing, for examination
"Well, I guess that's what a fellow
gets for stubtin' his toe when a kid,"
Dioa almost wailed the rejected would b
roveny, luuimesn, imi, mvmituo
and all the darker shades, of life may
be lighteuedi with transfigured glory
through the brightness of a smille.
Lamentation sobs itself Into silence,
tears are driven away, hope and joy
spring to life under the awakening
influence of a smiling, sympathetic
face.
"All this Is prelude to the subject:
The beauty and value of cherfuiness
in this old world of ours.
"The English government offered
Sj.OOO.OftO for the smile of the ten
der face of Mona Lisa. It could not
be purchased. Money could not buy
Its value was above rubies.
"So much for a , smile on canvas.
marine.
Sergent E. H. Galway, in charge ot
the local station, told him that he was
Anlu I .fi f nf tVlO .1 1 1 H IT A .1 nn!1 '
cants. Out of 14 during the pastweek
but two have been accepted. One
was married, others were too fat or
heavy, some n.ore than six feet one
inch tall, and others were deformed.
"Some time ago," Sergeant Galway
said, "a down-and-outer entered the
station and made application. His
white hairs gave him away, as he
posed as ' bein.? but aO years old, al
though he was more than sixty.
Corporal J. F. Clark, of Washing
ton, D. C. ariived Tuesday morning
to assist Sergeant Galway at the lo
cal branch.
There is a demand from the local
But. in real life nothing costs so lit
tle and is worth so much as the gen
,., r.Vrfiilnosfl nf n kindllv smile.
' . .. . branch for boys between 15 and 1
Learn from this story the real value v ,
of a cheerful face. Mona Lisa
has gone from the Louvre, but
thank God -the benediction of her
smile kindles many a face, and cheer
fulness still abides to lighten woe
and sorrow."</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 6-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1911-09-03/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 7-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/2010270509/1932-09-15/ed-1/seq-7/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 8-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1911-09-10/ed-1/seq-7/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE THEFT OF THE 'MONA LISA
rixmxi.s or the maiiistuatf
nno vi fstwatfii it.
I rand MMpMM That the Thief Npent
Hi. Malll In Ihr I Jim re A Crll Ic's
RNM far llcllexltiR thr Ural
Minis I .Ion " V n Nlnlcn lam llcfiirc.
"tHis. Sept. 2 The official Inquiry
into the atMllu of tlM "Mona UM'eloaed
fW day, lnet.tli.tlon and y. el ,
r cry slight results. M. Driotit, U
Miigiatrttt charged with holding the
-tu'ation (which like all preliminary t
oil
I'.imera), glvet the following account
i hi" work, which although it contain
little that haa not already heroine known
the fire I official itory of Hit robbery:
The Mona Lltg' Wat stolen on Mon
,! iy. August St, betWeet 7:2d und 82S in
- .'morning. On that day, about Tilt, the
foreman of the maeofM working in the
; inert pa teed through tht Carre nalon.
the aqttart hall where the picture hung.
hi company with a workman painler.
Icclerc. employed regularly liy lhe
inttaeum. Icclerc pointed to the 'Mar
rlage of C'ana,' the size of which la well
known, and eaid: 'There la a cunvua
which muat have coat dear ' Then point
ing to the Mona Lisa.' fatdened to the
wiill in face, he added: 'And to think
thai that little picture la even worth
ni re! They aay it ia the deareet in the
muatlUn,' The two men went up to and
looked at the work of da Vinci.
"A few minutcM later the foreman
maeon, paaeing again through the Carre
ilon. wiahlng to ihoW off hia knowledge,
repeated to tWO Of hia men what he hail
just learned 'The "Mona Llat," htaald,
i- not large, but it is the moat Valuable
thing here. It ia worth at least MOO.OOO,
Take a good look at It. baotutt it ia often
taken away to l,e photographed or If
repair! are heing made in the museum.'
At H: 1 6 Iheae two men passed through
lhe Carre salon again. The 'Mona Lisa'
i ni Bone.
1 here you are.' aaid one. he waa quite
i ;lit. They have taken it away already '
I auppoee it s because of the work
going on.' aaid hia companion Thus
tiie hour of the theft ia established in
,,n undoubtedly certain manner
"Almott at the same minute, ulioutiof
7 20. a Worklna plumber. Rauvnt. found I
thai the door of the Sphinx conrt waa i
opened, that a beginning had been made i
I unscrew the lock and thnt one of the
door knoba had dlaappeared. The Bphlns I
court, where the seven meter staircase
Is and where the modelling workshops
are. is above the Viaconti court.
"To keep to the chronological order,
about 7:30 o'clock (here the time is some
what less certain i a WitOttt saw a man
hurrying along the dry moat of the palace
toward the d'OraaV atation carrying a
packet about the size and shape of a pic
ture; then an employee of a large depart
inent store who was going to take a river
boat noticed some one. whom unfortu
natelr he can only (leeoiibe vaguely
It, row aom.-tl,intr into the m,, at six or ,
veil varda before the lirst opening f I
'
th" gacwav into the t'arrouael Souare
At first he attached no importance to
ihe set. but later after reading the papers
he thought he ought to apeak a1. out it.
But before that, on Thuraday. he wanted
to make sure that the object (he ilid not
know what it waai was still in the moat;
he went past the tppl and aaw the door
knob still there anil ajtuin passed later
iikthe day wh"ii it still was there.
"On Friday morning, by which time
he hail decided to come uml tell me about I
i' he again patted, but the knobbed gone. I
sweener a few mini ilea before had I
found it and handisl it to u museum wa' ch
inaii
ing '
it was easily Identified as belotig
the door; it bore the same iiiaiin-
ftcturer't mark. T. F . as the remaining
knob and fitted the lock exactly.
"Was the Individual who was seen
going toward the d'Orsuv station with a
packet under hia arm and who reached
th station a 7:47 o'clock and took the
J :50 express to bordeaux the robber?
All inquiries made in this direction have
given no. result. As for the clue of the
man who threw away the doorknob, the
detcriptiont and Information we have of
him, at least at present, are too vague to
allow me to follow it.
"What do I consider has been estab
lished since the legal investigation was
opened? First of all, I think we can put
aside without the least doubt any thought
of complicity by the maaons. house paint
ers, photographers and copyiata. As re
gards the last, it has been proved Uiat
they only arriv.si at the Louvre after the
picture was taken. And notably the
photographer of the Hrauu llrm were
occupied all the morning with MM. Bone-
due and Itoreux in the K.gvptian an
unties hall. I have verified minut.
il
how each one of these employed his time
jit will be noticed that M. Prion i carefully
excludes the 'gardiena' (the watchmen or
attendanta) from the category of those
hose complicity is to lw discurded.
"Was there complicity from the inside''
The truth oompela me to aay that no aeri
i us contradiction exists in the testimony
given by the staff Whether thai is due
10 the real facts or to an understanding
among them, until I have fuller infor
n ition I must consider the etatementt
ill the guardians as sincere Therefore
on the tieslion of complicity from within
I know nothing. I nave made or am
11 iking an Investigation into how each
mploeed his time who way on duty
r.iaht lietween Hundav and Monday
and Who was there or ousht to have lieen
t!ir the Monday morning. That ia all
I . an aav ,"
1 DrfoUl then (tlvee a fact which has
I i l.een made puhlie, at least as dell
llitely aa before
"Did the robber shut himself up In the
Louvre for the nlht between Sunday
and Monday? The investigations I bave
made leave no doubt t lint such a thing
QUitt possible There la all along
lbs Puohatel hall a dark niplioard, or
ret her reoeaa. wiiere iMiaela and stoola
ire stored The door was found open
dtny one rould easily have hidden there
,.l passed the night Hut I have found
i Idenotto trove that any one did so
Kxperlmente have tnown how easily
-ingle person who waa accuatomml to
il mg down the Mona l.iaa' could do
operation and in a very aliort time,
i how difficult it would be for any one
&OOUe tOlned to the operation."
m Prloui now atatea another fact
r'o not onVuily known, one thai
- the want of oart and aual alack --
with which the UnjVra haa been
i nasd,
s for the frame in Otrved wood, which
1 untetl of Hcarn presented, it waa
i -it the top of the etatrcaeo i have
n . i itddtnot of m Boutin, the
' "f the Louvre., who declares that
aaw the frnnie in thia place nil Mon-
.' 'ernoon alaiut 4 o'clock he attached
importance to this fact. Oil the glaas
' ' versd the picture we have found
fingei mark tin. only on,, we have.
" -t a i reuse we found the fattentrt
iipi-d like a Ion, S which fast snarl il,,.
.iiiil i lit
frame aiul one ot Uic screws
"'I. last, , , , .)., turn.
iislderable ialne to find out
siispii'ioue perann had lieen noticed
1 8rr Halnn 'iuriiiB the days pre-
'I.. Iheft, I was told that no one
raoted any particular attention
IS that, iven the manner In whirl,
It
,1
ties of guardianship are curried
'tiia museum. 1 should have been
I surprised if I had obtained
i Informatton mi tin-. point.
any exact
"There exists nt tin- LoUVfe n semi
official detective agency under M de
Mrtini'V, former committal re (,f polloe,
Hut not only arc these special ogents in
plain clothes not very numerous, lint tin v
are nut on duty the day the public in not '
admitted (a ni tht ram- the ilav of llie I
theft), nor nrv thev resinsiblc f'r ninht
icnity.
"Then is one tmitit to which l would
iik.' to draw attention. Mention haa been
! made of love letters which have been
written to the 'Mona IjIm. and It haa been
K'KfeMed that the robbery may have
SSSfSSrES
though I believe that paealon would have I
deetroyed In the guilty person the clear-1
'"'HH "' Ininking neceatary to carry put I
cms inexplicit!!).' liifii, I tiuin in'O'iilli
less ,,rclr in v tHt i r.ii 1 1 r i h i.. ne made in
r niveatii'aliotis t
t hia direction.
"My own opinion, however, ia that the
criminal im acted from love of gain
either on hia own account, hoping to n -aell
the product ,,l his theft. ,.r on accunt
of tome otic who haa bribed him and paid
him loyally
"However that may be I am abandon
ing the alt, ill of the Moiia Lisa' to take
up other mattera that 1 have on hand
I can only await the results of tht re
actrchce now being carri.nl on bv the
detective Service I hope aome new
fact will he discovered t or the moment
I have no clue I have no aerious clue
Home grounds on which the I'ricf. 'oris
basi-d its story, printed in -Inly. IBlo.
that the "Mona l.iaa" had been stolen
before that date and a copy sulwtltuti'd.
have been made public They cannot
be called convincing in themselve. al
though the ease with which the picture
haa now been stolen shows at leaat the
iKiasibility of the story being true
M Kphraim. the director of the t'rl
At "aria, nn amusing four cent weekly sa
tirical aheet. had received more than one
anonymous letter saying that a copy had
been aubatituted for the original of "Mona
l,isa " M Kphraim then asked a well
known art critic, Paul (.sell, to give an
expert opinion on the Picture, then in
the Carre Salon And It waa on faith
in this opinion that the Cri tie Vids made
its startling announcement, although
II will be seen that M Qttll made his
examination under conditions that robbed
it of much of its value M (isell says
"I examined the work very closely,
but 1 must cotifeas at the outset I hat
the ulaas with which it was covered
made my task qtlitt difliciilt Innumer
able ctfiectiona formed in it. and as the
painting behind the glass was sombre
it aoled behind the glasa like the tinfoil
behind a mirror and everything In front
waa visible on the glasa The imagea
of paaeertby, the velvet covered benches
In the centre of the salon, were certainly
much more distinct thau the feature
Mona
Lisa However, ufter Walking
right side and then from the
from th
left, after standing on my nptoee and
Using my bunds as a shade to prevent
,... nflaationa 1 ended bv c including
, That Ineteadof tht celebrated ex-
preeaion of mystic preteitnot winch we
all have recoifinzed 111 the true Mocolidi
the one I waa looking at had a finicking,
characterless smile, the smile of uny
charming little woman.
"II, liiut the execution, instead of
being free and bold ua in the old picture,
waa labored, worked up. pumice stomal;
'that it presented no marked tone; that
for example the clean touches which
showed the folds of the sleeves were
wanting; ihat tTTe cheeks and tiie Beany
partt Ol the hands did not displuy that
beautiful, generous inipaato the richness
of which I had many and maijtT a time
admired in the true Mona Lisa '
III. That the coloring generally was
buried if I lliav Use the expression; that
it wiia more soiniiro wian inai oi ine irue
1.. I.. (ha. I liu Hisih llMll tiAoollW M
Idirtv vellow and that the landscape
from the transparent blue in iJa Vinci s
original, had become a disagreeable
greenish color The whole effect, more
over, waa much more of a green tone
than In the true Joconde '
'I wondered if these results could la?
produced by the glass, and came to the
Conclusion that this glasa, however
alurhtlv It waa tinted (and all classes ui e
I more or leeel, might have changed the
Coloring I admitted too that the polish
'of the irlass might nave attenuated in
tones of the painting Nevertheless, the
modifications noticed, both in the coloring
and the technique, were too great to arise
solelv from the glass In nv case this
I glass could not have changed the ei-
praatlon or Nona i.isa. aim me maignin
oanoe of the smile that I was gaiug on
proved to me without a doubt that 1
was in fronv of a copy.
"I wrote tht articles which appeared In
the (iri 'una In July, ItlO I revealed in
them the fac that the 'Joconde' had been
stolen I begged that the glaas should
la removed to verify my assertion Need
less to say the udminiatration would
never consent M Homolle merely
shrugged his shoulders and told a news
paper man ttia! it was a poor jose even
to pretend that the 'Joconde' could be
stolen
"It may be objected against ray asser
tion that even under the glass it would
have been easy to verify tnat the paint
ing waa on Wood, like the original, and
thut the cracks in the paint were the same
as those shown by photographs taken
of the original To that I reply that
forgers always consider it their lirst care
to reproduce with great fidelity the
material character of any work ft was
an elementary idea therefore to siibsti
tutefor the true 'Joconde' a OOpyOnWOOd
in which the cracks were perfectly Imi
tated "
The Pnlrir has published R letter which
goes to confirm M. Qttfl'l theory, but its
value is lessened by being anonymous
The writer says:
"I am an artist and a picture restorer
and have between 19ol and 1003 restored
many paintings and engravings for M
Louis Heu.v, an antiquity dealer at St.
F.ticnne In 1009 M. frenzy brought me
two pictures to restore, one being an ex
cellent cotiv of the Joconde' on wood
When I delivered them back I not)
'i i
that two small spots of light green paint,
splashes from my palette, had fallen In
the background of the upper left side of
tht Copy, They were almost invisible
and it waa too late to efface them, so the
picture waa taken away in thia state.
"In July laat. visiting the Louvre, I
saw the Joconde' for the first time, cov-
1 with glass My attention was at
! tracted l.y two amall li?lit itreen murks
in the background ntgn up on ine icit.
I thought I must lie the victim of an
illusion and went buck to examine the
picture a dozen times. 1 waa not dream
ing; thoae were certainly my spota left
on the copy My conviction wna certain;
the true '.loconde' waa no longer there,
the copy I had handled in 190? had taken
ita place.
"1 kept my opinion to myself for the
affair was ttlioUl, To-day. when the
'Joconde' is stolen. I float
The I'alrit adds that In a second letter
t he writer saya "Tiie panel waa Worm
eaten and gave the impression it waa old
wood from a bed On the back of the
Ennol was gummed an old number of the
Woir Hvslre, dating from I him or IIU,
a picture on prtMiesa paper with an article
by Hoger Miles la-low. I waa SO struck
by these light green apota that 1 returned
every day for ten days to the Louvre,
aa i could not believe my eyes I nm
abaolutejy convinced that the 'Joconde'
stolen lately waa only an admiral; opy
It will be noted that the writer llxeaihcrs of the uaaociatloii in all lh" sliopa
hia viait to the laaivre aa during the
month f July, the date tht Cri dt Parle
punllinea ita announcement, " is vnvre-
fore possible that suggestion may play
iinconacioiisiy
conviction.
some pari in the whim
Japanese Amliasasilor Preparing to He
turn lo Toklo,
W'ashinoton, Soot II Haron Yttauyu
Ul hida, the Japtneee Amhoaautlor, has
rttumtd to Washington to pack up his
household effecta preparatory to icturn
ing to T'ukio to accept the post of Minis
ter of roreign Arrairs oi etpan lie win
sail from Seattle on September 21. Mus-
anuo Huniharu, Firal Secretary of the
embassy will act as Charge it'ArTnires
during the Ambassador's alwence and
until nis successor Is named Neither
lhe Stale Department nor tho embassy
hua received word us to who the new
Ambassador will be
NEW ZEALAND BALKS AT "SIR"
axtipiwe t.v.s t itr a xgeeeo
.iorni tints TITLE,</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 9-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87062268/1911-09-09/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Stolen Potrait of "Mono Lisa,'' for Which $5,000,000 Was Refused
Paris, Sept. 8. The announcement
that Leonardo Da Vinci's famous por
trait of Madonna Lisa del Gtoconda of
Florence, known as the "Mona Lisa.
the costliest painting in the world, had
been stolen created a tremendous sen
sation here, Parisians being said to
have forgotten for the time the rumors
of war. Great crowds collected In the
neighborhood of the Louvre, where for
five years the painting has been on ex
Investigate the story told her by him
respecting the early marriage of the
artist, who realizes he has made an
awful blunder.
However the artist may view It, the
friends of the young woman do not
feel that this Investigation will dis
close anything that will Improve his
present unpleasant poosltion which
they regard as Indefensible.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	  <!--extra document 10-->
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85038485/1924-03-30/ed-1/seq-47/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
	  </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
